<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Propositions, tending to proove the necessarie vse of the Christian Sabbaoth or Lords day; and that it is com... vs in Gods [wo]rd. VVherevnto is added the practice of that sacred day, framed after the rules of the same word. By Iohn Sprint, an unvvorthie minister of the Gospell of Iesus Christ, at Thornebery in Gloucester shire.</title>
            <author>Sprint, John, d. 1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12801</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103198</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838955</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838955</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3348</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12801)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3348)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1220:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Propositions, tending to proove the necessarie vse of the Christian Sabbaoth or Lords day; and that it is com... vs in Gods [wo]rd. VVherevnto is added the practice of that sacred day, framed after the rules of the same word. By Iohn Sprint, an unvvorthie minister of the Gospell of Iesus Christ, at Thornebery in Gloucester shire.</title>
                  <author>Sprint, John, d. 1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By H. L[ownes] for Thomas Man, ..,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1607]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device (McKerrow 278) on title page.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lower margin of A1, title page, cropped, with loss of imprint date; some print lost on title page; signatures F3-4 bound out of order following A1.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sunday --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3348:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3348:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:3348:2"/>
            <p>Propoſitions, TENDING TO PROOVE THE NE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie vſe of the Chriſtian Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth, or Lords Day; And that it is <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vnto vs in Gods</hi> WORD. WHERE VNTO IS added the Practice of that ſacred Day, <hi>framed after the rules of the ſame</hi> WORD. <hi>By</hi> IOHN SPRINT, an vnvvorthie Miniſter of the <hi>Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, at</hi> Thornebery <hi>in Glouceſter ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Humphrey Lownes, framed device of an open book surrounded by beams of light; below the initials of Peter Short, whose device this previously was (McKerrow 278)</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q>ET VSQUE AD NVBES VERITAS TVA</q>
               </head>
               <p>P. S.</p>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Man,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3348:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:3348:3"/>
            <head>The Summe of all, in one Syllogiſme.</head>
            <p>That the Lords daie, or Chriſtian Sabbaoth, is <note place="margin">The Lords Day</note> neceſſarily to bee obſerued by all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to the end of the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hatſoeuer dayes obſeruation was in the Newe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sanctified by</note> 
               <hi>ſanctified, and ſet apart to an holy vſe:</hi> 
               <note n="1" place="margin">Chriſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</note> Firſt, by Chriſt his triumphant reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <note n="2" place="margin">Chriſts firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parition.</note> Then, by his firſt appearing to his gathered Apoſtles &amp; Diſciples, fiue times on that ſame day. <note n="3" place="margin">Chriſts ſecond apparition.</note> Next, hy his ſecond appearing to his gathered A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. <note n="4" place="margin">Holy Ghoſt apparition.</note> Fourthly, by his ſending of the Holy-Ghoſt to his Apoſtles gathered againe, and bleſſing of their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine by conuerſion of ſoules. <note n="5" place="margin">Command ordinance of poſtles.</note> Fiftly, by Apoſtolicall Commaund, &amp; Conſtitution, to be obſerued by Chriſtian Churches. <note n="6" place="margin">Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandement.</note> Sixtly, by Chriſts Commaund, not to be profaned of anie faithfull Chriſtian. <note n="7" place="margin">Practice of poſtles.</note> Seuenthly, by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles ſolemne practice of preaching, miniſtring the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments in the Chriſtian Congregation, and meditation of the Scripture. <note n="8" place="margin">Title giuen the Holy-Ghoſt</note> Eightly, by the holy-Ghoſts induing it with a notable &amp; peculiar title of the Lords day. <note n="9" place="margin">Practice of and the moſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Churches.</note> By Apoſtolicall, primitiue, and all later reformed Churches general and continual practice, from thence vnto our times. <note n="10" place="margin">Iudgeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the moſt ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all &amp; godly l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned.</note> By the iudgement of the ſpirituall &amp; moſt godly lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Teachers and Writers of the former and later ages. <note n="11" place="margin">Effectes Gods bleſſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> By the witneſſe of Gods generall and continuall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the practice therof, with peace of conſcience, ioy of the Holy-Ghoſt, and ſenſible increaſe of knowledge and
<pb facs="tcp:3348:4"/> grace in all ſincere Chriſtians, that with ſoundneſſe prefeſſe the Goſpell euery where. <note n="12" place="margin">Diſlike and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>anation by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e wicked and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſound.</note> And laſt of all, by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and oppoſition of the onely moſt wicked of life, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of mind, or otherwiſe vnſound in iudgement and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.] <hi>The Obſeruation of that Day is moſt neceſſary, and doth tie the Conſcience to the end of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But ſuch is the Obſeruation of the Lords day, or first day of the weeke; and ſo confirmed in euery point. Therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The holy Obſeruation of the Lords day or firſt day of the week, is moſt neceſſarie, and doth tye the conſcience to the end of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Propoſition confirmed.</head>
               <p>For the firſt member: Look Section, 56, 55. For the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, third, fourth, ſeuenth, and ninth: Look Sect: 61. For the fift and ſixt: Looke Sect, 58, 59. For the eight: Looke Sect. 55, 54, 59, 60, 64. For the tenth, eleuenth and twelfth: Looke, Sect, 65.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Proofes of the Aſſumption in the ſeuerall members.</head>
               <p>The 1. There is no queſtion of this point: but that Chriſt roſe on the firſt day of the weeke.</p>
               <p>The 2. That Chriſt appeared 5 times on that firſt day of the weeke; which was the day of his reſurrection, and of the Chriſtian Sabbaoth: firſt, to <hi>Mary Magdalen. Mark.</hi> 16 9. <hi>Io.</hi> 20. 14, 15, 16, 17, 18. Secondly, to the woman: <hi>Mat.</hi> 28, 9, 10, 11. Thirdly, to the two Diſciples: <hi>Luk.</hi> 24. 18. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 13. Fourthly, to <hi>Peter: Luk.</hi> 24 33. 34. with 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15, 5. Fiftly, to the eleuen: <hi>Mark.</hi> 16. 14 Excepting <hi>Thomas: Io.</hi> 20. 24. Wherein our Sauiour dooth comfort, inſtruct, authoriſe, and ordaine the Miniſters of the Newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and giues them power to preach and adminiſter the Sacraments &amp; Diſcipline. <hi>Io.</hi> 20. 22. 23. with <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. 15. 16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 16, 17, 18, 19, 20. This was performed in the night: partly by Chriſts appointment: <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 16. Partly for feare of the Iewes, not daring to aſſemble by day. <hi>Io.</hi> 20. 19. The day notwithſtanding ſanctified by Chriſts fiue fold appearing; and the Diſciples holy meditation &amp; conference of and with Chriſt.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3348:4"/>
               <p>The 3. That CHRIST appeared the ſecond time on that day ſeuen-night (Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ing, comforting, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing, reproouing) appeareth; <hi>Io.</hi> 20. 26, 27, 28, 29. Where it is ſayd, after eight dayes (including and counting the day of Chriſts reſurrection for one of the eight, which is that day ſeuen-night:) as if he ſhould ſay the eight day after: by an Hebraiſme. The like ſpeech in <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. 21. &amp; 1. 59. <hi>Leu.</hi> 12. 3. Thus <hi>Caluin, Beza, Piſcator, Rollock,</hi> take it: and ſo do the very Papiſts, <hi>Ferus, Ianſenius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel Sa.</hi> vpon theſe places.</p>
               <p>The 4. That the Apoſtles met vpon this very day (the firſt day of the weeke, on the morning; <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 15) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, becauſe they met on the day of <hi>Pentecoſt. Act.</hi> 2. 1. with <hi>Leu.</hi> 23. 15. 16, called the feaſt of weekes. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 22. Which was the morrow after the Sabbaoth. <hi>Leu.</hi> 23. 16. 15. This alſo, the computation of Weekes betweene the feaſt of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and <hi>Whitſontide</hi> dooth prooue: For it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: as if one ſhould ſay, the fiftieth day. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 1. becauſe fiftie full dayes, or ſeauen weekes are to paſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the feaſt of <hi>Eaſter</hi> or Paſſeouer (the day after which, Chriſt roſe) and the feaſt of <hi>Whitſontide</hi> or of weeks: <hi>Leuit.</hi> 23. 15. 16. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 22. on which day the Apoſtles now met. For this truth, look the iudgement of <hi>Auguſtine, de tempore ſer.</hi> 251. <hi>Nazianzen apud Baroniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Leo Ep.</hi> 81. <hi>&amp; Concil. Conſtantinopol.</hi> 6 <hi>Caluine, Beza, Piſcator:</hi> with the Papiſts. <hi>Bellarmine de cultu ſanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. See <hi>Emma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel Sa. annot. in Act.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>Baronius Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>ex Nazianzen.</hi>
               </p>
               <l>The 5. Look for the confirmation thereof. Sect. 58. 59.</l>
               <l>The 6. Look for this, Sect<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 64.</l>
               <l>The 7. Look for this alſo: Sect. 60. 61.</l>
               <l>The 8. Look for this, Sect. 59. 55. 54. 60. 64.</l>
               <l>The 9. For this look Sect. 15. 20. 63. 62.</l>
               <l>The 10. Is prooued Sect. 15. 20. 34. 52.</l>
               <p>The 11. and 12. Is confirmed by palpable experience: and apprehended by him that eyther hath an eye, or win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not: Look for theſe, Sect. 65. and the fowre laſt Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alſo.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3348:5"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3348:5"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any matters (Chriſtian Reader) called into queſtion at this day, are offered to the viewe of the World; and not a fewe of them very fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous and vnprofitable: but there are alſo matters which doubtleſſe cannot bee denied to bee of ſingular importance for the furtheraunce of our moſt holy faith and true Religion. And amongst the waightieſt of theſe, there is almoſt none of greater vſe nor of more neceſsity to be vnderſtood, nor being vnderſtood to bee more carefully obſerued then this which hereafter enſueth touching the nature and quality of the Lords day commonly called Sunday or the Chriſtian Sabbaoth. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which, there are diuerſe, who (not by reaſon of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny difficulty in this controuerſie, but) being led with the variable conceit of their owne vnſettled minds, do think diuerſly: and many ſuch there are who doe ſpeake and wright thereof ſo looſely, yea ſo profanely, that if their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions were imbraced among men, there could nothing but Atheiſme and irreligious behauiour growe vp there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by and abound. Sundry of theſe points this Treatiſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing doth with great diligence lay open vnto thy conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; and withall ſetteth downe plentifully a true and right reſolution of this matter. Namely, that the firſt Day of the weeke (called Sunday, as before ſayd) is
<pb facs="tcp:3348:6"/> in a peculiar regard, the Lords day, and ſanctified to the performing of the ſolemne worſhip of GOD, vpon the grounds of Gods Morall or perpetuall lawe in the fourth Commaundement of the Decalogue; And by the ſpeciall will of Christ eſtabliſhing it through his Apoſtles prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice &amp; doctrine to the ſame purpoſe, inſtead of the Iewes Sabbaoth. Which Aſſertion certainly, if it were well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and belieued, would make very effectually to the great increaſe of godlineſſe, and to the cutting downe of much ſinne and impiety; which euen by meanes of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and neglect hereof doth euery where ouerflowe. The Lord in his good time will diſpell the errors and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of vngodly men, and wil aduance in greater bewtie the kingdome of his ſonne Chriſt, by diſſoluing the works of Satan, and treading vnder foote all his malice. In the meane while, it behooueth the ſeruants of God to be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant (and nothing ſlacke) in ſhewing forth the wiſdome of Serpents, aſwell as the ſimplicitie of Doues: That they being wiſe in the truth, may cauſe the ſame to ſhine among others in theſe euill dayes; and yet withall in their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie may find fauour not with God alone, but alſo with men. Reade, trie and holde faſte that which is good: and the Lord giue thee vnderſtanding in all things. <hi>Farewel.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3348:6"/>
            <head>PROPOSITIONS tending to prooue the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie obſeruation of the Lords day, <hi>or Christian Sabbaoth.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N handling of this Queſtion of the Chriſtian Sabbaoth: I purpoſe to ſpeak in order of three things. Firſt of the ſtate of the controuerſy. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, of the arguments and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for the truth. And laſt of all, the anſwere of obiections.</p>
            <p n="2">2 There be two different iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments concerning the Sabbaoth: the one in extreamity, the other in the meane.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The iudgements, or rather the opinions, ſtanding in extreamity are extreamly oppoſite and contrary: and they are holden by men of ſuch quality, as are otherwiſe branded with the note of infamous hereſie.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The one extreame is of them, who holde: that there ought to be no Sabbaoth or difference of dayes, nor anie certaine time or day appointed for reſt, and publique mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3348:7"/> for Gods ſeruice: but to leaue it as a matter meerely fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for euery one.</p>
            <p n="5">5 They alleage for themſelues, 1. That the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anchius de oper. redempt. li.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 19. <hi>fol.</hi> 608. <hi>Vrſinus Cathech<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>art.</hi> 3. <hi>ad quaeſt:</hi> 103. <hi>fol.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>79 Rogers di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>play of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Family of loue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n a confeſſion of one of that ſect §: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> is meerely ceremoniall. 2. The Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: whereby we may, where and when we liſt, worſhip &amp; ſerue God. And as we are freed from the circumſtance of place: <hi>Io.</hi> 4. 21. 23. So are we alſo (ſay they) freed from the circumſtance of time of ſeruing God. 3. They alleage Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: as <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> 2. 16. <hi>Galathians,</hi> 4. 10. <hi>Romans,</hi> 14. 6. <hi>Matthew,</hi> 12. 8.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The Authors of this looſe opinion are the Family of Lone, ſayth <hi>Rogers;</hi> and the Anabaptiſts, ſayth <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 Theſe men (ſayth <hi>Zanchius) abutuntur Scripturis,</hi> abuſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zanch. vbi ſupra. fol.</hi> 608. 611. <hi>Vrſin. vbi ſupra.</hi>
               </note> the Scriptures, and conclude from them that which cannot be concluded: Whom he confutes, as alſo doth <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 But to paſſe by this irregular ſect, and ſalt vvhich hath loſt his ſauour; I ſay with him: <hi>Iniquum eſt &amp; impium aut nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los eſſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zanch. Ibid. fol.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>12.</note> 
               <hi>aut qui ſunt, contemnere.</hi> It is impious and vngodly, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue no certaine dayes of Gods publicke ſeruice, or to contemne thoſe that are appointed and eſtabliſhed. So teach (ſayth he) the Scriptures, the Fathers, and godly Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of our later age: and ſo doth the auncient receiued and approoued cuſtome and practiſe in all Churches, of all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and nations confirme.</p>
            <p n="9">9 The other extreamity of opinion, is of thoſe who hold: that the Iewiſh Sabbaoth of the 7. day in the week from the creation, is neuer to be aboliſhed; being no leſſe neceſſary for vs to obſerue now, then it was euer for the Iewes.</p>
            <p n="10">10 They alleage reaſons drawne, 1. From the praece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Sabbaoth before the lawe, and before the fall: the Lawes of which nature are immutable. 2. From the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity of the Morall lawe. 3. and from the large extent ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of appertayning to all. 4. From the perpetuity of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. 17. 5. and of the cauſe of the lawe which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it perpetuall: which is the memoriall and meditation of the workes of God: which belonges vnto the Chriſtians, as well as to the Iewes.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3348:7"/>
            <p n="11"> 11 Theſe reaſons in themſelues are good: but, being miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applyed to the eſtabliſhment of the Iewiſh ceremoniall Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth which was a ſhaddowe of things to come, and is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed: <hi>Conatus eorum tanquam peſtilentiſſimus</hi> (ſayth <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Muſcul. Loc. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> part.</hi> 1. <hi>fo.</hi> 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>eſt retundendus:</hi> their indeuours as beeing moſt peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent are by all meanes to bee ſuppreſſed; Both becauſe (ſayth hee) they obſcure the glory of our Sauiour by reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Lords day, and bringing Chriſtians as much as in them lyes, vnder the yoke and ſlauery of the Moſay call lawe againe.</p>
            <p n="12">12 The Authors of this vnchriſtian opinion: are either Iewes as <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vrſin. Cath. in praecept.</hi> 4. <hi>ad quaeſt</hi> 103. <hi>fol.</hi> 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7, 76<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vrſinus</hi> ſayth: or <hi>Ebion</hi> and <hi>Cherinthus</hi> as <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jrenaeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Irenae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiphan. hereſ.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Epiphanius</hi> witneſſe: or Sabbatary Chriſtians; as <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Muſcul. loc. part</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 145. 146. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Muſculus</hi> &amp; <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Beza. Theſ. Gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenſ. c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. §. 15</note> 
               <hi>Beza</hi> ſay: or Anabaptiſts as <note n="f" place="margin">Gryſaldus Peruſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Haere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cor. n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bus. Titul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sabb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarij.</note> 
               <hi>Gryſaldus Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſinus</hi> (a Papiſt) doth report; and are confuted by <hi>Muſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Vrſinus,</hi> and <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar: Tom:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>li.</hi> 3. <hi>de cultu ſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> cap.</hi> 10</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13 The iudgement ſtanding in the meane, is of ſuch Churches and perſons (from the Apoſtles age to ours) as withall profeſſing the truth and ſoundneſſe of the Chriſtian faith, haue in all times &amp; places, without interruption, que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion or gaineſaying kept holy, and eſtabliſhed the Lords day, being the firſt day of the weeke from the Iewes Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth.</p>
            <p n="14">14 And theſe are eyther primitiue or later: wherein by the way wee will conſider of the middle or neuter ſort: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the primitiue and later: namely the Papiſts, and their iudgement.</p>
            <p n="15">15 The auncient primitiue, and orthodoxe Fathers, both Greeks and Latines, doe with one mouth certifie vs of theſe ſoure things touching the Chriſtian Sabbaoth day. <note n="1" place="margin">
                  <hi>Baſil: de ſpirit ſancto. c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoſt: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om.</hi> 43, <hi>in</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cor. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>guſt. ſerm de Tempor:</hi> 251. <hi>Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m contra Fauſt li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 32, <hi>cap.</hi> 11, <hi>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cil: Colonienſ par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 9, <hi>cap</hi> 9</note> The originall thereof: which they ſay was firſt eſtabliſhed by Chriſts owne bleſſed and inſpired Apoſtles. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ignatius epist: a Magn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſios. Iuſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Martyr. Apol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Col. Atha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t. de verb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> de circumciſ. &amp; Sabbat, Chriſoſt. ſerm</hi> 5. <hi>de reſurrec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cil. generale. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Conſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tinop. can. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 86. <hi>ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p.</hi> 119. <hi>c.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Idem de c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. l</hi> 22. <hi>c.</hi> 30. <hi>Idem de verb. Apoſt. ſerm.</hi> 15, <hi>Idem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Tempore. ſerm.</hi> 251. <hi>Iſidor, ded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>Bed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Luc.</hi> 24.</note> The cauſe or occaſion: in memory of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſurrection of Chriſt our Lord (who roſe vpon that day) &amp; of his triumph ouer death
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3348:8"/> and hell. <note n="3" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ignatius &amp; Iuſtinus vbi ſupra Irene: li.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 19, 20, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2, 33, 34. <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onyſius Cornithacus apud Euſeb. Eccleſ. h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt. i.</hi> 4, <hi>c.</hi> 23. <hi>Orig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es hom.</hi> 3, <hi>in Exod: &amp; contra Gelſum: li.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Cyrill: in Ioan: li.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 58. <hi>Tertullian: Apolog. ca.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9 <hi>Idem de Idolol: Hieronym. in vita Paule. Idem Epiſt. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtoch. Ambroſ. ſerm.</hi> 62. <hi>Auguſtin. Tract.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>in Ioan. Gregor. l.</hi> 11. <hi>Epiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. concil color. part</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 9</note>. Their honorable teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, generall approbation, and continual practiſe or ſanctifying of the ſame in their ſeuerall times. 4. And laſtly their effectuall eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof by all lawes: <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>In decret. de conſecrat. diſt.</hi> 3 <hi>can.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>&amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Decreta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it. de ferij<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ca.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l Laod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. c.</hi> 49. <hi>Concil. Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 47, <hi>concil A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſiod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. c.</hi> 16. <hi>Concil. Aurclianeuſ. c.</hi> 27. <hi>Concil. Conſtantinop.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 8, <hi>Synod. Auguſtenſ. c.</hi> 18. <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l. Mogunt. Can.</hi> 25, 14, 36, 37, 61. <hi>Tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an can.</hi> 19. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. c.</hi> 18. <hi>Matiſcon:</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>canc. l. Par ſienſ. lib.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>cap.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. <hi>Colonienſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> part.</hi> 9. <hi>ca.</hi> 9. <hi>Arelat.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enſ.</hi> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 40. <hi>Rh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>menſ. cap.</hi> 43. Booke of the Iniunctions of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Church of England: <hi>anno</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz. Ini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 20, 33, 38, 6. Booke of aduertiſements. pag. 8. <hi>b.</hi> 1. Canons 15, 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 14, 15, 21, 24. Canons. 1603. <hi>can.</hi> 34, 44, 45, 46 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7, 59.</note> 
               <hi>Canon:</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>In cod. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>de ferijs. Leg.</hi> 3. <hi>Theodoſij. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag.</hi> 10. <hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nis &amp; Anthen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>j. &amp; Leg.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. <hi>Valenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>j.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 9. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nor: &amp; Theod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Lex Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ni. Lib. ordination<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Caroli.</hi> 5. <hi>li.</hi> 2. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>bric.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 359</note> 
               <hi>Ciuill:</hi> and <note n="c" place="margin">Canutus Law. <hi>Lex</hi> 14, 15. Edgars Law Act. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on <hi>elit:</hi> 15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. <hi>fol.</hi> 14. a Law <hi>anno</hi> 27. <hi>Henrc.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 5 Actes of Parliament of Scotland ſince King Iames the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 20. Octob. 1579. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. King Iames the 1. his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamation 1603, againſt the profaning of the Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th.</note> 
               <hi>Common</hi> (as we tearm the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) eſpecially in this famous Iland of great Britaine.</p>
            <p n="16">16 The Papiſts comming be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the primitiue and later puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>(like a nettle growing between two ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes)</hi> as they kept (among other things) the letter of Gods word, the matter of Baptiſme, and doctrine of the Trinity: ſo haue they done (as they receaued from hand to hand in their ſeuerall times) the time &amp; doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Lords day. And yet as euery truth that hath paſſed thorow their hands in that their generall defection from the faith &amp; fore prophecied Apoſtaſie: So this alſo of the Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Catech. Rom. part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. in</hi> 3. <hi>praecept. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct.</hi> 21. <hi>Cataneus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ath. Rom. fol.</hi> 234 <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aniſ. Cathec. c.</hi> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>11. <hi>fol.</hi> 84. <hi>Vau. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>athec. c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>fol.</hi> 53. <hi>eliſius de</hi> 3. <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pt. fol.</hi> 315. 317. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rynaus diſp. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g. anno.</hi> 1598. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>harad. Chriſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heſ.</hi> 103. <hi>fol.</hi> 124. <hi>Tolet inſtruct. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rdot. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 24. <hi>fol.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>40. 541. 542. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>45. 546. <hi>Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us fol.</hi> 305. 306. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>07. 310. 315. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>17. <hi>Catancus in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>athec. Rom. fol.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>35. <hi>&amp; in ſunt.</hi> 1. <hi>Feſt. fol.</hi> 185. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Catheth.</hi> c. <hi>fol.</hi> 53.</note> hath pitifully been defiled, like pure water running through a muddy ceſterne.</p>
            <p n="17">17 For touching the time therof, they euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly profane it by <hi rend="sup">d</hi> horrible idolatry, wil-worſhip, maſſe-worſh, bread-worſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Saint-worſhip, Image-worſhip; and other myſteries of their Antichriſtian hypocriſie. As alſo by their impious <hi rend="sup">•</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of ſeruile labours, as butchers, bakers, fiſhings, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and repairing bridges, highwaies, Churches, teaching profane Arts and liberall ſciences, Lawyers, ſtudyings, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and informing cauſes euen for gaine, fayres and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets: as alſo their teaching of the lawfulneſſe of vaine and wicked recreations and paſtimes, as ſword playing, carding, dauncing, fiddlers muſick euen for gaine: and almoſt what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is confirmed by the diuers cuſtome of euery place, or indulgenced to them by the Popes large licence.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3348:8"/>
            <p n="18"> 18 And neither hath the doctrine of the Chriſtian Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth eſcaped free from their corruption. For albeit with one mouth they acknowledge rightly, <note n="1" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cathech. Rom. part.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>in pracept.</hi> 3 <hi>ſect.</hi> 4. 14. <hi>fol.</hi> 319. 322. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſius. Confeſ. Petrie v. fol.</hi> 300. <hi>c.</hi> 79. <hi>Rhem. Teſt. in Apec.</hi> 1. 10.</note>. That the Lords day was by the Apoſtles themſelues eſtabliſhed: and that (as <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Feliſius fo.</hi> 292. <hi>ex Auguſtino. ep.</hi> 119 <hi>ad I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n. c.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Fauſt. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ch. l.</hi> 32. <hi>c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. <hi>&amp; ſerm.</hi> 251. <hi>de Tempore.</hi>
               </note> ſome of them doe ſay) <hi>Dominico <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſſu:</hi> by Chriſts owne commaundement, <note n="2" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cath. Rom. fol.</hi> 322. <hi>in</hi> 3. <hi>praecept.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 14. <hi>Bellar. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>de cultuſanct. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 10. 11. <hi>Feliſius fol.</hi> 290. <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. in Apoc.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>Vaalx cath. c.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 51. <hi>Ribera. in Apoc.</hi> 1. 10.</note>. That this was done by them in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of Chriſt his reſurrection. <note n="3" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cath. Rom. part.</hi> 3. §. 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 319. <hi>Bellarmi. Ibid. c.</hi> 11. <hi>Fel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſius fol.</hi> 29<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Rhem. Teſt. in Act.</hi> 20. 16. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1. 10.</note>. That the places. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 7. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1. 10. do manifeſtly confirme this day. <note n="4" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. Ib d. c.</hi> Io. 11. <hi>Stella in Luc.</hi> 14. <hi>fol.</hi> 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>a.</hi>
               </note>. That it is a day aboue all other dayes to be eſteemed. <note n="5" place="margin">
                  <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llar. Ibid. c.</hi> 10. <hi>Rhem. Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. in Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>&amp; Mat.</hi> 15. 9. <hi>Eccius Enchirid. Tit. de feſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nijs. fol.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>34.</note>. And laſt of all that the obſeruation thereof is, <hi>Iuris diuini, pars cultus diuini;</hi> and dooth tye the conſcience: yet all this they affirm; to conclude here hence their Churches falſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited authority without the word of God: and that the obſeruation of this day, neither is <hi>Iuris dinini;</hi> nor yet doth tye the conſcience otherwiſe, then as it is commaunded by the Church: and ſo by conſequence is but a meere tradition of vnwritten verity. For they ſay it hath no commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, neither Legall nor Apoſtolicall.</p>
            <p n="19">19 The latter ſort of Orthodoxall Churches and perſons are ſuch, as commonly are tearmed of the Proteſtant profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Who being led by the ſelfe ſame ſpirit &amp; word of God, <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13. 12. Phil. 3. 15.</note> and yet being men, whoſe degrees of knowledge are limited and different: doe in the moſt materiall points conſentingly agree, in certaine circumſtances differ, each one abounding in his ſeuerall ſenſe.</p>
            <p n="20">20 The materiall points, wherein they doe all of them ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally agree touching the Lords day, are chiefely theſe; <note n="1" place="margin">
                  <hi>Muſcul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Loc. vol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. in</hi> 4. <hi>praecept. fol.</hi> 147. <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Caluin: inſtit. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>ſectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> 31. 32. <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger: Decad.</hi> 2. <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rm.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 125. <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Martyr. Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 7. <hi>claſſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>Idem in</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. <hi>fol</hi> 444. 6. <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Beza. Theſ. Geneuenſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 39. <hi>ſect.</hi> 8: 9. <hi>Idem i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Argumento Pſ.</hi> 92. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Reu.</hi> 1. 10. <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Zanch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> de redemptione. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>fol.</hi> 610. <hi>c.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Vrſinus Cathee. ad queſt.</hi> 103. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>art.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>66. <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Moſis c.</hi> 8. <hi>fol.</hi> 117. 118. 119. 120. 121. <hi>Idem pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lect. in Geneſ.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 63. <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>. Exa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> part.</hi> 4. <hi>de ſeſtu fol.</hi> 697. <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Heming. Symagma, edpracept</hi> 4 §. 12 <hi>fol.</hi> 362. <hi>&amp; Enchirid.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Lex. claſſ.</hi> 2 <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Hyperiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1. 2. <hi>Pezelius Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, part.</hi> 3. <hi>fol</hi> 169. <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Sadiel. contra artic. ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rat. &amp; reſp. art.</hi> 49. <hi>fol.</hi> 500. ¶ 2. Tome of Homilyes. <hi>fol.</hi> 258 the firſt parte of time and place of Prayer. ¶ Nowel: Catech. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>fol.</hi> 95. 96. ¶ Deerings Lecture 19, on Heb. 4. 10. <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Fulke Rhem. in Apoc.</hi> 1. 10. <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Perkins, in Gal.</hi> 4. 10. <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liffe: pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ma fides inſtit. fol.</hi> 11, ¶ Babington on Com. 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>68.</note>. That the fourth Commaundement is partly morall and perpetuall: and partly ceremoniall proper to the Iewe, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3348:9"/> quite aboliſhed. 2. That the ceremoniall of that Law ſtood <note place="margin">12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>Bullinger: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſculus &amp; relequi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rd omnes locu ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> in the ſeuenth dayes reſt from the creation; the ſtrictneſſe of that reſt; the ſhaddowing of Chriſt to come and reſt in the graue, which was performed on the Sabbaoth day; and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſh ceremonies and ſacrifices tyed vnto their obſeruations of it. 3. That the publicke worſhip of God, preaching and hearing of the word, adminiſtring &amp; receiuing of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and prayer, together with the workes of mercy, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing reſt to Seruants and to Cattell vpon a certaine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined day (to vvhich ſome adde the limit of the time; one <note n="**" place="margin">
                  <hi>Martyr. Iunius: Hemingius:</hi> F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lke: Perkins: Babing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on. <hi>Vbi ſupra. Muſodus Iludem fol.</hi> 146. <hi>Beza confeſ. de Eccleſ. c.</hi> 5. §. 41. <hi>fol.</hi> 157. <hi>Wolph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. l.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcator expoſit. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thech. in</hi> 4. <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> 120. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. in Coloſs.</hi> 2. 16. <hi>fol.</hi> 1. 64. and his Lecture 19. on Coloſſ. 2. 16. Nowels Cathech. <hi>fol.</hi> 99. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 12. <hi>fol.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>12. <hi>Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>in Matt.</hi> 10. <hi>f.</hi> 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Book of Hom. <hi>fol.</hi> 258. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> day of 7.) is the morall of the fourth Commaundement and of the law of Nature belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging to vs, as well as to the Iewes. <note n="4" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. The. Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. c.</hi> 39 §. 12. <hi>fol.</hi> 84 <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>not. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Reu.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>Zancheuede redemp. fol.</hi> 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. <hi>a. b. Clematiue: loc com. part.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 61. <hi>v. Viſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. part.</hi> 3. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 103 <hi>fol.</hi> 767. <hi>Iunius prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 63. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ad Gen.</hi> 2. 3 <hi>&amp; Cath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch. f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. <hi>Sade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Hem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius. Pezelius:</hi> Fulke: Perkins: Babington. <hi>vbi ſupra. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x Meditat. in. Apoc.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>Buch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> prel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rn. fol.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Hyperius in Heb.</hi> 7. <hi>fol.</hi> 327.</note>. That the Apoſtles of Chriſt did them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues tranſlate the Iewiſh Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth into the Lords day. <note n="5" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bullinger. Pezelius. Martyr. Muſculus. Beza. Zanchus. Chemnitius. Iunius. Piſcator. &amp; rel quiſerè <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Item vid. plura hac dere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ione</hi> 58.</note>. That this tranſlation by the Apoſtles, is to be prooued and concluded di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly out of thoſe places of <hi>Act.</hi> 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 1. <hi>Corm</hi> 16. 1. <hi>Reu.</hi> 1. 10.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="6" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nger. Martyr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator. Pez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lius.</hi> Fulke booke of Homilyes, <hi>&amp;c. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſupra. Hyperius in Hebr.</hi> 7. <hi>fol.</hi> 327. <hi>Gualter in Act.</hi> 10. 7. <hi>fol.</hi> 259 <hi>Aretius in A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oc.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note>. That this alteration was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made both to put a differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betweene the Iewes and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: as alſo in memoriall of our Sauiours reſurrection. <note n="7" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zanch. de Redemp. fol.</hi> 610. 628. 629. 630. 632. <hi>Bulling. Dec d. fol.</hi> 128. 129. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 702. 703. 704. <hi>Holuetica <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. <hi>Tome. fol.</hi> 260. <hi>Perkins pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> fol.</hi> 231. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopſ. fol.</hi> 429. 430. <hi>Zepperus dep. litera eccle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. fol.</hi> 94. 95. 96. 97. 98. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>per on Commaund. 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 45. <hi>Babington in co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 171.</note>. That the primitiue Churches Fathers and Chriſtian Princes, did in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall times alwayes obſerue and cauſe to bee obſerued the Lords day with all holy ſolemnity and godly reuerence. <note n="8" place="margin">
                  <hi>Brentius in Le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uitic.</hi> 23. 2. <hi>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r in Mat.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. <hi>fol.</hi> 112. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rm. confeſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. <hi>Gualter in Act.</hi> 20. 7. <hi>Hom.</hi> 132. <hi>Zanchius de Redempt. fol.</hi> 610. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note>. And laſtly, that the Lords day is by no meanes to be contemned, but hath well and rightly beene obſerued by themſelues and others heretofore from the Apoſtles, and hereafter to the worlds end, aboue all other dayes; ſeeing it is the receiued and confirmed manner: the which muſt needes be better and more fit then any.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3348:9"/>
            <p n="21"> 21 This harmony of iudgement in ſo many perſons of ſo great excellency and worth, and that according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in theſe concluſions, albeit I gaineſay not, but there may be found among the rubble of the ruins of Gods Image, men of ſo palpable abſurdity and nothingneſſe of common ſenſe, that doubt not to ſway againſt them all: and vvith one negatiue to batter their authority &amp; weighty grounds: yet bee that farre from euery ſober minde and honeſt heart. Such Cyphers of men do open but a gap, to caſt off any thing neuer ſo foundly concluded by the godly learned, to bring in nouelties, and to make an Idoll of their owne conceipts: and therby manifeſt vnto the world their pouerty of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, of iudgement and of conſcience: which kind of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe argueth plaine giddineſſe of head, profaneneſſe of hart, and a ſchiſmaticall, priuate, and praepared ſpirit to any head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe error or braine-ſicke haereſie.</p>
            <p n="22">22 The points of difference among the godly learned, doe ſtand in three diſtinct queſtions: the one depending on the other: Firſt, whether the keeping holy of the ſeuenth day, or any one day ofeuery ſeauen, be part of the Morall lawe of God, and bee perpetually to be obſerued. Secondly, whether the Lords day, or firſt day of the weeke (called commonly our Sunday) bee eſtabliſhed <hi>iure diuino:</hi> by the wil and ordinance of Chriſt, in ſtead of the Iewiſh Sabbaoth, and do tie the conſcience. Thirdly, whether the Church of God might haue choſen at the firſt another day, or hath yet authority or Chriſtian liberty to abrogate or alter the Lords day into any other certain or vncertaine day: or whether it be not of neceſſity to be continued to the end of the vvorld. Some there be that affirm, and other ſome deny.</p>
            <p n="23">23 The <hi>Tenents</hi> of either ſide, for aſmuch as they are both of moſt reuerend mention, and bleſſed memorie; and yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene an affirmatiue and negatiue of the ſelfe ſame thing there can be but one truth (which we are commaunded dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to try and follow) I wil propoſe their difference, with as much ſincerity &amp; truth, and diſſent from that which ſeems the weaker, with as much modeſty as I may.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3348:10"/>
            <p n="24"> 24 And doe profeſſe my ſelfe in this point of the more ſtrict part: yet with ſubiection to the ſpirits of the Prophets in the Church of God. Beeing ready to yeelde to any man that will refell my reaſons and inſtruct mee better: hauing (by Gods mercy) learned in modeſty to iudge of my ſelf and others, and to follow the truth in loue &amp; peace, as in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the iudge of all the world.</p>
            <p n="25">25 The ground of my perſwaſion is the euidence of <hi>Truth</hi> appearing to my conſcience, being chayned to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the preſent Church of <hi>England</hi> (of the which body I reioyce I am a member). The which kind of motiue is to me of double force: I ſay the authority of the viſible Church of God, being ioyned to the truth: which is no leſſe waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with, then it is light without the truth of God. It is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in the ſecond <hi>Tome of Homilyes,</hi> the which is mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the booke of Articles.</p>
            <p n="26">26 And this mention of the differing iudgements of moſt reuerend men, agreeing in the ſubſtance of Religion, is not propoſed to ſet them together by the eares, or to try the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of eyther ſides authority (For how ſhould one eſcape the note of inſolence and pride, and want of humble charity and ſober wiſedome): But onely to acquaint the Reader vvith the needefull grounds, and ſimply to propoſe this matter, as rather ſeeking truth then victory or cauſe of wrangling.</p>
            <p n="27">27 Neither dooth this difference of iudgement praeiudice the doctrine of the Goſpel. For, by the one part, the Iew gets none aduantage, ſeeing they vtterly renounce their legall Ceremonies, ſtrict reſt, and ſeuenth day (counting from the Creation): Neither the Libertine by the other, ſeeing they make it morall and perpetuall to obſerue ſet daies, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue alwayes kept the Lords day holy, counting it impious to profane or breake it by contempte or negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, vntill the Church hath greater cauſe to alter it, then the Apoſtles had to appoint it, and command it.</p>
            <p n="28">28 Nor of this diuiſion (or the like) hath the deluded Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt any thing to boaſt. For if they ſpeak but one halfe word
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3348:10"/> heerein, wee will preſently intreate them to keepe them on their dung hill; and firſt pull out the beame from <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm: Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cultu ſanctorum Tolet: Inſtruct ſacerdot. li.</hi> 4. <hi>ca</hi> 24. <hi>fol.</hi> 542. <hi>Perkins: proble<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tit. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s fest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. fo.</hi> 231. <hi>Chemnitius loc: com. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ars ſecunda ad</hi> 3. <hi>praecept. fol</hi> 61. 62</note> and <hi>Tolets</hi> eye: who ſway with <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Caietane</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtreame of <hi>Scotus, Soto, Abulenſis,</hi> and the other Schoolemen, about this very matter of the Chriſtian Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth. So might wee deale with them in matters of controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies; for there are few or none depending betweene them and vs, wherein they differ not among themſelues, and like the foure windes blowe in one anothers face. Aske <hi>Bellarmines</hi> three Tomes whether I lye or not, and aske withall where is the Catholique vnity they boaſt of.</p>
            <p n="29">29 But you ſhall obſerue (about this controuerſie of the Lords day) the former ſort &amp; company of reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; godly Writers (for moſt part) liuing in the times next aboue vs, of the more remiſſe and weaker iudgement: and the later, of the more ſincere and ſtrict; God (as it were) rewarding the diligence &amp; paines of euery age, with the reuealing of ſome part of truth: and alwaies fiery and pearcing wits omitting nothing to oppoſe or to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the truth; which by tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> means hath by degrees been manifeſted. The which thing as he did to them in other times before, reuealing to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſundry truths whereof their Predeceſſours neuer were acquainted (each faithfull one profeſſing purely the holy truth he ſaw) ſo dealt he with the primitiue Fathers in their ſeuerall times, and ſo (perhaps) will doe with them that followe vs: ſo hath hee done vnto this age of ours: and as he hath reuealed ſundry other truths; ſo alſo this of the Chriſtian Sabbaoth.</p>
            <p n="30">30 The occaſion of this difference in the former, was the oppoſition, that they bare againſt the Papiſts, the maine and only aduerſaries (in a manner) of thoſe times: who impoſing on the conſcience a neceſſitie of all the rabblement of their ſuperſtitious and Idoll dayes, and the like Will-worſhips and meere humane Traditions by the Church authority: Our reuerend VVriters oppoſe to them againe the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an liberty: <note place="margin">Caluin: Bullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ter. Bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius: Chemnitius. Vrſinus: &amp;c.</note> by the which liberty (ſay they) the Apoſtles and Apoſtolicall Church altered the Iewes Sabbaoth into the Lords day, by which the preſent Church may alter it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3348:11"/> (on iuſt occaſion) into another day: and by which wee are freede (ſay they) from obſeruation of all dayes, other then ſuch as ſerue for neceſſarie ſeruice of GOD, and order in the Church.</p>
            <p n="31">31 The later iudgement doth ariſe from the oppoſition of another kind of Aduerſary, cleane differing from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. I meane the Atheiſt, Libertine and carnall Goſpeller (inſeperable vermine of euery eſtabliſhed and ſlouriſhing free Church, ariſing chiefely from the ſweate and rankneſſe of plenty and proſperitie, and abſence of the Croſſe): for as the one is choaked with the ſmoake of ſuperſtition, and is prodigious in the number and quality of dayes and other Ceremonies; ſo the other is drowned in profaneneſſe, and breake the cordes and bands of God himſelfe aſunder, and will not haue the Chriſt of God ro reigne ouer them. From hence, the later writers (abounding in another ſenſe) preſſe <note place="margin">Beza, Iunius, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcator, Rollock. Fulke, &amp;c.</note> a neceſſity of a Chriſtian Sabbaoth, and ſo do differ from the former: Neceſſity compelling thereunto. For as the Papiſt blotteth out the 2. Commaundement, and ſayth it is but ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Catharinus li. de imaginibus: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Bellar. tom.</hi> 1. <hi>li.</hi> 2. <hi>de imag. cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Beza: theſ. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nev. ca.</hi> 36. §. 15</note> poſitiue and temporall; euen ſo the carnall Goſpeller (ſtraining the bands of Chriſtian liberty till they be burſt) blotteth out the fourth Commandement, and ſayth it is but ceremoniall. Why might not now the Atheiſt and periured perſon blot out the 1. and 3. and like wiſe ſay, they be but ceremoniall?</p>
            <p n="32">32 And ſo hauing vnfolded the ſtate of the quaeſtion; and ſpoken of theſe other needfull circumſtances: I will proceed to eſtabliſh the truth of my perſwaſion, and then will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the obiections.</p>
            <p n="33">33 The firſt member of the truth, in this controuerſie, is this: <hi>That the keeping holy vnto God, of one day of the</hi> 7. <hi>of euerie weeke, is apart of the Morall lawe of God, and by all Chriſtians to be obſerued to the end of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="34">34 This propoſition is affirmed by <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide annotata ad</hi> §. 20. <hi>Bullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in Rom.</hi> 14. 5</note> 
               <hi>Muſculus, Martyr, Beza, Iunius, Hemingius, Bucer, Wolphius, Piſcator, Rollock, Fulke, Perkins, Nowell, Babington;</hi> and by the Church of England in the 2. Tome of <hi>Homilyes.</hi> But is denyed by ſome
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3348:11"/> others; by affirming that the Church may alter the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the ſeauenth day into the number of the 10. or 14. or any other day, as iuſt occaſion is offered.</p>
            <p n="35">35 The affirmatiue is prooued by theſe Reaſons. The firſt Reaſon: becauſe the obſeruation of the ſeauenth day, is of the lawe of Nature, whatſoeuer is found in the fourth Commandement appertayning to the lawe of Nature, as a thing moſt godly, moſt iuſt, and needefull for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth of Gods glory, it ought to bee reteyned and kept <note place="margin">2. Tome of Homil. <hi>fol.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Martyr. I. oc. claſſ.</hi> 2 <hi>ſect.</hi> 2 <hi>Iunius prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Gen.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 3. 63. <hi>Muſculu Loc. com. part in</hi> 4. <hi>praecept. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 147.</note> of all good Chriſtians. But in the fourth Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is found the obſeruation or keeping holie of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day, or one day of the vveeke, as a thing moſt god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, iuſt and needefull for the ſetting forth of Gods glorie. Therefore it ought to bee reteyned and kept of all good Chriſtians. This argueth the Church of England: <hi>Martyr, Iunius &amp; Muſculus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="36">36 The ſecond argument ſtands in this: becauſe as there muſt be a certaine place, ſo alſo there muſt be a certaine time for the publick exerciſe of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; without the which (ſaith <hi>Bullinger)</hi> the externall worſhip cannot be performed vnto <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bulling. Dec ſerm.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 1 <hi>Caluin. inſt a ca.</hi> 8. §. 32.</note> God: but all would run (ſayth <hi>Caluin)</hi> vnto ſpeedy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euitable ruine and confuſion. Now for deſining the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time, who can better proportion it then God himſelf? who in the time of mans innocency bleſſed the 7. day (that is; did deſtinate it to his ſeruice) and in the Morall lawe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed it to the lewes: who better then the Sonne of God, <note place="margin">Book of H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 2. Tome. <hi>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 260.</note> and his inſpired Apoſtles, who did apportionate vnto his Church one day of ſeauen; as 1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 16. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Therefore by this reaſon it ſeemeth, that the ſeauenth day is perpetually to be obſerued.</p>
            <p n="37">37 The third Reaſon. Becauſe the obſeruation of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen day conformeth vs vnto the Image of God, of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles; who alwayes reſted the ſeauenth day, and kept it holy in that proportion: which in another propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">Book of H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Tom. 2. <hi>fol. Caluin. inſt ca.</hi> 8. §. 31. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyr. loc.</hi> 7. <hi>cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſect.</hi> 2.</note> deſtroyeth Gods holy Image in vs in that point. This Image of God is propoſed in the fourth Commaundement <hi>[For in ſixe dayes.]</hi> Therefore to conforme our ſelues to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3348:12"/> the Image of God, wee are to keepe holy the ſeauenth day: and not to doe it, is to deſtroy that part of Gods Image in vs.</p>
            <p n="38">38 The fourth Reaſon. Becauſe the ſanctification of the ſeauenth day, conformeth vs to the Image of <hi>Adams</hi> holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in his integrity: to which, albeit wee cannot perfectly attaine in this life: yet we are to ſtriue vnto it, becauſe he was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zanchius de eribus creatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. part.</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 1 <hi>fol.</hi> 480.</note> created to the Image of God, holineſſe. Therefore to ſtriue vnto the Image of <hi>Adams</hi> holineſſe, wee are perpetually to obſerue the 7. day holy vnto God * as <hi>Adam</hi> did.</p>
            <p n="39">39 The fift Reaſon. Becauſe the end of the 7. dayes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ſeator in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.</hi> 2. 3. Dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g: Lect. 29. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Heb. 4. 10.</note> is perpetuall, namely to worſhip God, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in his knowledge. Therefore the obſeruation of the 7. day muſt alſo be perpetuall.</p>
            <p n="40">40 The ſixt Reaſon. Becauſe the ſame neceſſity is vnto vs, that was to <hi>Adam,</hi> the Patriarches, and the lewes, to keep holy a 7. day. The ſame neceſſity in reſpect of God, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of vs no leſſe proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſeruice, then he did of them. In reſpect of Gods Church, the which needeth no leſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>illinger Decad. Iſerm.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 5.</note> of order. In reſpect of our ſoules, which need no leſſe proportion of meanes to be inſtructed and ſanctified: In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the bodies of our ſelues, our ſeruants, and our Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, that alſo neede no leſſe proportion of reſt, then they. Therefore the 7. dayes holy reſt is of neceſſity to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
            <p n="41">41 The ſeauenth Reaſon. Becauſe the obſeruation of a longer diſtance then a 7. dayes reſt, woulde proue iniurious to our ſelues: our ſoules: our bodies: the ſoules and bodies of our ſeruants: and the bodies of our cattle. For ſeeing God hath giuen ſuch a portion and proportion of time to vs and ours to ſerue God, and be profited in ſoule and body: as it was Gods double mercy to grant it, ſo it would be a double cruelty to with hold it, or depriue vs of it.</p>
            <p n="42">42 The eight Reaſon. Becauſe it derogateth from the wiſdome of God, of Chriſt, and his inſpired Apoſtles: who proportionating ſo much time vnto our reſt, ſo much vnto Gods ſpeciall and publicke ſeruice, and ſo much euen to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3348:12"/> labouring ſeruant and drudging beaſt, as knowing what was fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>teſt for euery one; it being meaſured out by Gods owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence according to their ſtrength: If the Church ſhould breake this proportion, and alter it to the 10. or 14. it coulde not but commit much error, both in croſſing of Gods hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly and moſt perfect wiſdome and appointment, as alſo in breaking of the due proportion.</p>
            <p n="43">43 The ninth Reaſon. Becauſe we may not profane that day which God ſanctified; for ſo ſhould wee turne that day into a curſe which God hath bleſſed: But God ſanctified and bleſſed the 7. day, both in the lawe of Nature, and Morall lawe; both before the Ceremoniall lawe, and out of it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. Now it is in his onely power to abrogate the obſeruation of the ſeauenth day, that ſanctified it: but God neuer abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated the 7. dayes obſeruation. Therefore we are perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to ſanctifie the ſeauenth day.</p>
            <p n="44">44 The tenth Reaſon. Becauſe the fourth Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſanctifying one day of 7. is not Ceremoniall, but Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and perpetuall: which Chriſt deſtroyed not. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 17 which the Apoſtles eſtabliſhed. <hi>Rom</hi> 3. 31. This point is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by 6. Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="45">45 Firſt: whatſoeuer Lawe was peculiarly written vvith the ſinger of God, and that in ſtone: and that two ſeuerall times immediatly deliuered by God as no other lawes Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall or Ceremoniall were, and euen put into the Ark of God with the other 9. Commaundements: <hi>(theſe circumſtances implying their permanencie euen vnder the Goſpell,</hi> and the deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of any power but Gods to blot them out) is as perpetuall as other Lawes ſo written &amp; reſerued: But, ſo was the fourth Commandement written and reſerued; no Ceremoniall or Iudiciall being ſo. Therfore the fourth Commandement is as permanent as the other nine.</p>
            <p n="46">46 Second: That lawe, that was eſtabliſhed before Chriſt was promiſed or needed to be promiſed, cannot be Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall or haue reference to Chriſt to come. But the obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the 7. day was eſtabliſhed before Chriſt was promiſed: Therefore the obſeruation of the ſeauenth day is not Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3348:13"/> but of the lawe of Nature, Morall and perpetuall.</p>
            <p n="47">47 Third: It implyes a playne abſurdity, to thinke that the wiſdome of God ſhould write, in two Tables of ſtone, 9. morall lawes, and but one ceremoniall. Therefore to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way this abſurdity, we muſt conclude it to be vniforme with the reſt, and morall as the reſt.</p>
            <p n="48">48 Fourth: The morall lawe is Gods conſtant and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Couenant &amp; direction of good workes. The perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Couenant of God was written in 2. Tables, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of 10. words, <hi>Exo.</hi> 35. 28. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 13. But if the Church ſhould take away one of the 10. there would be left but 9. &amp; ſo one of the words of God, and lawe of the perpetuall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant and direction of good workes would be aboliſhed.</p>
            <p n="49">49 Fift: From the Reaſons of the obſeruation mentioned in the 4. Commandement. For albeit there are ſundry rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in other places which God giueth as proper to the Iews, wherfore they ſhould obſerue the Sabbaoth, (as 1. their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance from the ſlauery of <hi>Aegypt, Deu.</hi> 5. 15. 2. that it was a ſigne that the Lord ſanctified <hi>them</hi> and was <hi>their God:</hi> and therfore it is called a ſigne to <hi>you</hi> and <hi>your generations. Exo.</hi> 31. 13. <hi>Ezec.</hi> 20. 12. 20.) Yet in the 4. Commandemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, he giueth reaſons onely common to vs as well as vnto them. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 11. As namely, 1. conformitie to Gods Image; which is no leſſe proper to vs. then to the Iewe. 2. <hi>Memoriall</hi> of Gods creation; for which benefit the Patriarches before &amp; the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſince are no leſſe bound to be thankfull vnto God, then was the Iew. 3. <hi>Reſt,</hi> of our ſelues, our ſeruants and our Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell; a common neceſſitie to vs, as it was to them. Therefore this Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement ſeemeth morall and giuen vnto vs aſwell as to the Iew. And ſeeing the Reaſons of this 4. Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment do vrge vs aſwel as the Reaſons of the 2. 3. &amp; 5. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, why ſhould not this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement tie vs to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of it, as well as the other? and why not Chriſtians as well as Iewes?</p>
            <p n="50">50 To which, I will adde the circumſtances notable in this Commaundement aboue all others. 1. That there is no Commaundement, except the 2. (as our reuerend Maſter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3348:13"/> 
               <hi>Greenham</hi> noteth) in words larger, or in reaſons fuller then this of the Sabbaoth. Which two Commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts the Lord did know would moſt of all be withſtood, as beeing moſt contrary to the wiſedome of the fleſh: the one oppoſed by exceſſiue ſuperſtition, the other by immoderate profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. 2. The precepts of the fourth Commaundement are both affirmatiue and negatiue: which in the other are onely affirmatiue or negatiue. 3. There is praefixed a <hi>Memento</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 8. which note is not praefixed to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and is a note (as <hi>Caluin, Muſculus, Zanchius</hi> and others teach) of eſpeciall obſeruance, requiring more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry attention and heedfulneſſe of practiſe. 4. No ſuch parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, or ſo many as in this one: 1. of the perſons to obſerue it <hi>[Thou; thy ſonne, and daughter: Man and maide-ſeruant: cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell and ſtraunger.]</hi> 2. of the reaſons: <hi>God hath giuen vs ſixe dayes. It is the Sabbaoth of the Lord, thy God. The Lord in ſixe dayes made the world, and reſted the ſeauenth. The Lord hallowed the ſeauenth day.</hi> 3. Of the works: one negatiue, excluding all. <hi>[Thou ſhalt doe no manner of worke.]</hi> one affirmatiue, excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the workes of the Sabbaoth. <hi>[Keepe it holy.]</hi> The which circumſtances, ſeeing they were ſet downe and made obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable and notable to vs by the vnſpeakeable wiſedome of God, and placed in the center (as it were) of the other 9. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Commandements: vndoubtedly the Lord would neuer ſo vehemently haue perſwaded fleſh and bloud to this, by ſo many circumſtances aboue al other, had it bin only ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, and not alſo morall. And ſo much of the firſt queſtion.</p>
            <p n="51">51 The 2. queſtion of this controuerſie is this: <hi>Whether the Lords day or firſt day of the weeke</hi> (called commonly our <hi>Sunday,</hi> though with a note of diſlike by the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Beza annot. ad</hi> 1. Cor. 16. 1. <hi>Fulke: in Rhem. Test. ad Apoc.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>Willet Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopſ. controu.</hi> 9 <hi>quaest.</hi> 8. <hi>part.</hi> 2. <hi>error.</hi> 72. <hi>f.</hi> 435.</note> godly lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) <hi>bee establiſhed</hi> iure diuino, <hi>by the will and ordinance of Christ, in the ſteade of the Iewiſh Sabbaoth, and doe tye the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="52">52 This quaeſtion is affirmed by <hi>Beza, Iunius, Piſcator, Rollock, Hooper, Fulke, Perkins,</hi> and the book of <hi>Homilyes</hi> and <note place="margin">Locis ſupra cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> others: But is denyed by ſome others.</p>
            <p n="53">53 The Papiſts alſo are at oddes about this very point.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3348:14"/> For <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tolet. Inſtruct. ſacerd. li.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 24 <hi>fol.</hi> 542.</note> 
               <hi>Scotus,</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Perkins. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem: Tit. dies Feſti. fol.</hi> 231.</note> 
               <hi>Panormitan, Angelus, Sylueſter,</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Feliſius in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 292.</note> 
               <hi>Feliſius,</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>de cultu ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum. li.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 19</note> 
               <hi>Soto, Lyranus, Abolenſis:</hi> and generally all the <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chemnitius Loc. com. parte ſecunda ad prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 61. <hi>a. b.</hi>
               </note> Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men doe affirme it: But the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> do vtterly deny it. And <hi>Tolet</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> do pitifully fall vpon the Schoolemens bones, and vtterly defie that ſentence.</p>
            <p n="54">54 But the affirmatiue, which I haue vndertake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by the following Reaſons. The 1. Reaſon. Becauſe <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 8. Chriſt is called the Lord of the Sabboath: the word is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. In the word is to be noted. 1. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, and 2. Propriety: and therefore <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1. 10. it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. the Lords day: as beeing Lord (that is the Owner and Commaunder) of that day. Now, in that Chriſt is the Lord, that is the Commaunder; I conclude, Chriſt therefore commaunded and ordained it: or at leaſt in that Chriſt is the Lord, that is the owner of it, thus I argue: Therfore it muſt be conſecrated to Chriſt his ſeruice. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God the Father was Lord of the Sabbaoth, there was a Sabbaoth neceſſarily kept vnto that Lord of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth: and ſo the Commaundements, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 8. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58. 13. did tye the conſcience: So alſo when the Sonne of God is Lord of the Sabbaoth: there muſt of neceſſity be a Sabbaoth day ſanctified, and thoſe morall commaundements doe no leſſe belong to Chriſt, and tye the conſcience of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an in the newe Teſtament; then they belonged to God the Father, and tyed the conſcience of the Iewe in the olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</p>
            <p n="55">55 The ſecond Reaſon. From the Image of God which is in Chriſt, <hi>Io.</hi> 5. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Whatſoeuer things the Father doth, the ſame things doth the Sonne alſo: But the Father ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a day vnto the glory of his work of the Worlds creation. Therefore the Sonne doth alſo ſanctifie a day vnto the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his worke of the Worlds renouation. Againe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 10. Chriſt ceaſed from his workes, as well as God the Father did from his. Therefore Chriſt is to haue his Sabbaoth or reſt ſanctified, as well as God the Father. Againe, <hi>Io.</hi> 5. 23. <hi>All men ſhould honour the Sonne of God, as they honour the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> But all men honour the Father with a day of holy reſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3348:14"/> and worſhip (in the old Teſtament) and it was a ſpeciall part of his honour. Therefore all men muſt honour the Sonne of God, with a day of holy reſt and worſhip <hi>(in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment).</hi> Chriſt therfore being honored by hauing aſcribed to him the Word, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3. 16. Sacraments, <hi>Acts.</hi> 8. 16. and 10. 48. &amp; 19. 5. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 24. 25. 26. Prayer, <hi>Io.</hi> 16. 23. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 1. Why not alſo with the Sabbaoth or day of holy reſt? ſeeing he aſcribes it to himſelfe. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 8. And, as Chriſt is called the Lord. <hi>Io.</hi> 20. 18. 25. 28. and 21 7. 15. 16. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23. and the phraſes are proper that runne after this tenor: the Lords Table. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 21. The Lords Supper. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 20. The Lords Cup. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. The Lords body. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 27. 29. The Lords death. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 26: So it is not vainly but moſt properly ſaid. The Lords day. <hi>Reu.</hi> 1. 10. as properly aſcribing it to Chriſt the Lord of Lords.</p>
            <p n="56">56 The third Reaſon: <hi>A Matori.</hi> If the reſt of God the Father were the cauſe of ſanctifying of a day: It followeth that where a greater and more excellent reſt is, there muſt of neceſſity followe a more ample ſanctification. But the reſt of the Sonne of God is a greater and more excellent, by how much the worke of Redemption is greater and more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then the worke of creation: Therfore the reſt of Chriſt from his worke is the cauſe of a more ample ſanctification of the day of his reſt or Reſurrection, which is our Lords day, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1. 10. Againe, If there be the ſame cauſe and reaſon of ſanctifying that day, on which our Sauiour Chriſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed our Redemption and reſtitution of the World, as there vvas of ſanctifying the day in vvhich the Lord reſted from the creation of the World: then a day in memoriall of the later ought as neceſſarily to be obſerued and ſanctified, as the day was in memorial of the former. But the ſame cauſe or reaſon remaineth (whether wee reſpect the reſt of Chriſt, as well as the reſt of the Father. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 10. Or whether wee reſpect the glory of Chriſt, as well as the glory of the Father: <hi>Io.</hi> 5. 23.). Therfore the day of Chriſt his reſt or reſurrection <hi>(which is our Lords day)</hi> is no leſſe neceſſarily by vs to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued then the former Sabbaoth of the Iewes. Briefly thus:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3348:15"/> If the very reſt of God the Father bee alleaged as ſufficient <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 15. 15. <hi>and</hi> 16. 13 <hi>&amp;</hi> 14. 26. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 20. <hi>♌ Vide ſupra.</hi> §. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 <hi>Num.</hi> 4. Hooper on the 4. Com. <hi>fol.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. <hi>Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r in Geneſ.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 52.</note> cauſe to ty the Iews co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience to the ſanctifying of the Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Sabbaoth: Then the very reſt of Chriſt may be alleaged as a iuſt cauſe, to tye the Chriſtians conſcience to the ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying of the Chriſtian Sabbaoth: but the former is true, as <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 11. Therefore the later is alſo true.</p>
            <p n="57">57 The fourth Reaſon. The Apoſtle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ordinances, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements and conſtitutions are the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements of Chriſt: <hi>Act.</hi> 15, 24. 28. 29. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 37. &amp; 7. 17. &amp; 11. 16. 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3. 6. 7. <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 16. For (beſides) the Apoſtles in matter of Gods ſeruice were led by the holy Ghoſt into all truth, and coulde not erre. But the Iewiſh Sabbaoth (in practiſe) was altred, and the firſt day of the weeke eſtabliſhed and ordayned for the Chriſtian Sabbaoth, by the ordinance, conſtitution, and commandement of the inſpired ♌ Apoſtles. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1. 2. <hi>As I haue ordayned, ſo do you:</hi> which words, ſay <hi>BB. Hooper</hi> and <hi>Piſcator,</hi> do plainly imply a commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: as the words, <hi>I haue ordained,</hi> do imply an Apoſtolical ordinance. Therfore the Chriſtian Sabbaoth or firſt day of the weeke was (in prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe) ordained and commanded by Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="58">58 The fift Reaſon: Is drawne from the euidence of ſcriptures plainly declaring that the Lords day was both or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and practiſed by the Apoſtles &amp; Apoſtolicall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches (to whoſe examples our Churches &amp; Chriſtians are and ought in all godlineſſe to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formed). The places are <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſtom, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Gualter, Aretius, Beza, Geneua note Lyra, Eraſmus, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablus, Emmanuel Sa. Rhem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſts in hunc locum. Chemmnit. Martyr, Zanchius, Vrſinus, Piſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tor, Iunius, Pez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us, Fulke, Babington, Perkins, Zepperus: in loc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s citat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorati Enchiridio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Tit. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es dominicus. Bucholch. Chron. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> proleg. f.</hi> 22. <hi>Bellar. vbi ſupra. cap.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 7. <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſost. Ambr. Hierom. Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g. Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſius. Theophilact in hunc locum Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. epiſt.</hi> 119. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>Beza. Bullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Martyr. Areti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Pezelius, Gualter Geneua note, Lyra. Eraſmus, Vatablus, Emmanuel Sa. Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, in hunc locum Chemnitius, Zanchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Vrſinus. BB. Hooper, Piſeator, Zepperus, Iunius, Bucholcher. Marlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorati Enchir. Fulk</hi> Booke of Homil. <hi>Babing. Bellar. Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſius, Cathec. Rom. locis citat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Sutcliffe in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tit fide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. fol.</hi> 11.</note> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 2. <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lemens. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtol. Ignatius, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinus, Tertullian Clemens Alexand. Orig. Athan. Ambr. Hieronym. Auguſt. Gregorius Magnus, Leo. Hylarius, Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius, Primaſius, Anſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. Martyr, Bulling. Beza, Iunius, Chemnitius, Zanchius, Sade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l, Vrſinus, Pezelius, Heming. Piſcator, Aretius, Bucholcher. Marlorati Enchirid.</hi> Book of Hom. <hi>Fox, Fulke, Babington, Perkins, Sutcliffe. Geneua note. Lyra, Bellarmine, Cathech. Rom. Emmanuel Sa. Rhemiſts, locis citatis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Reu.</hi> 1. 10. Interpreted all of them of the Lords day, by all (few or none at all beſides) expoſitors. 1. Fathers, Greekes and Latines: 2. Later writers Proteſtant and Papiſt: without diſputation or deniall. The concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this reaſon is; Therefore the obſeruation of the Lords day is no Tradition or vnwritten verity, or doubtfull ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but hath cleare ground and warrant of the word, and ſo dooth tye the conſcience. So alſo doe the duties and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances that out of theſe places may clearely bee conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3348:15"/> As namely, 1. That it was named, by an inſpired A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, the Lords day; which is as much to ſay, as the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Sabboth. Reu.</hi> 1. 10. 2. It was ordeined alſo and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by an inſpired Apoſtle, not lightly, vainly, or erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandingly with Apoſtolicall authority. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1. 2. 3. It was the firſt day of the week. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 7. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1. 2. 4. This aſſembly was weekly. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1. 2. 5. It was vſuall to other places and times: <hi>viz.</hi> the Churches of Corinth and Galatia 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1. 2. of Troas. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 7. of Pathmos where <hi>Iohn</hi> was: (and that aboue 40. yeares after, <hi>Reu.</hi> 1. 10.) 6. That day the word preached: the Sacraments adminiſtred &amp; Praier. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 7. &amp; 10. 16. 7. That day the works of mercy and collections for the poore. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 10. 12. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1. 2. 8. That day they reſted from the ordinarie labors of their calling. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1. 2.</p>
            <p n="59">59 The ſixt Reaſon. Is drawne from the enumeration of circumſtances notably falling out, (yet not in vaine, but to ſome neceſſary purpoſe; nor yet by chance but by Gods ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular prouidence and appointment, as may appeare by the greatneſſe of the works) vpon this day. 1. The reſurrection &amp; Reſt of Chriſt vpon this day. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24. 6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 10. 2. Chriſt his firſt apparition to his Diſciples vpon this day. <hi>Io.</hi> 20. 19. 3. Chriſt his ſecond apparition to them that ſame day ſeuen-night. <hi>Io.</hi> 20. 26. 4. The holy Ghoſts apparition to them on that day. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 1. 2. 5. The Apoſtles teaching &amp; miniſtring the Sacraments on the ſame day. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 7. 6. The Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> his inſpiration and reuelation that ſame day. <hi>Reu.</hi> 1. 10. (I omit the collections of the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſtin de tempore, ſer.</hi> 251 <hi>Leo Epist.</hi> 81. <hi>ad Dioſcor: Concil. generale</hi> 6. <hi>ſine Conſtantinop.</hi> 6. <hi>can.</hi> 8. <hi>Vide Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. <hi>de cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu ſanctor.</hi>
               </note> Fathers, as that this very day is the firſt day of the worlds, the Angels, and elements, and lights creation: the firſt of <hi>Manna</hi> falling in the wilderneſſe, the day of Chriſts natiuity &amp; baptiſme; of the ſtarres appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at Bethlehem to the wiſe-men: of Chriſts feeding 5000. perſons, &amp; the like. And fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence we may obſerue the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Sabbaoth by the Apoſtles which hath cohaerence with theſe circumſtances: To ſhew vnto vs partly the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability that Chriſt did ſanctifie the 1. day of the week him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: and partly that it was his ordinance and will, that that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3348:16"/> very day ſhould bee ſanctified by Chriſtians. For, 1. vvhen the Apoſtles, on this day, were gathered together for feare of the Iewes, <hi>Io.</hi> 20. 19. Chriſt then appeared vnto them. Why ſo? Doubtleſſe at that time aboue all others, to trayne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp in the ſanctifying of the new Chriſtian Sabbaoth day; and therefore alſo on this very day doth he inſpire them and indue them with the holy Ghoſt. And note the word, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>coacti,</hi> Gathered together; which implyes a Church aſſembly: for it is a word of Eccleſiaſticall vſe and ſo apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 8. and 4. 31. and 11. 26. and 13. 44. and 14. 27 and 15. 6. 30. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 4. The Primitiue is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> From thence <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 2. The Apoſtles ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond gathering together is performed on this day, the day ſeauen-night after, <hi>Io.</hi> 20. 26. And then alſo Chriſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to them; and then is <hi>Thomas</hi> confirmed in the fayth. Why the Apoſtles gathered? Why Chriſt appearing vnto them? Why vpon that day? but that they had learned of Chriſt to meet vpon that day to ſanctifie it vnto Chriſt: and that Chriſt might begin to verefie his promiſe. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 20 3. The Apoſtles third gathering together, and they all in <hi>one place with one accord,</hi> which was that day ſeauen weekes, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 1. 2. after Chriſts aſcenſion, and then the promiſe of the holy Ghoſt came vpon them. <hi>Acts,</hi> 1. 4. Then <hi>Peter</hi> preacheth, and the Iewes are aſſembled and conuerted. Why aſſembled? Why on that day? Why the holy Ghoſt? Why Preaching? why Conuerſion? why the promiſe of Chriſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, all on that day? but ſtill to declare the will and ordinance of Chriſt in ſanctifying and bleſſing this day vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Church. 4. The Apoſtle <hi>Paules</hi> fourth gathering of the Chriſtian Gentiles Church at <hi>Troas.</hi> And there he preached and adminiſtred the Sacrament, and cured <hi>Eutichus</hi> (a worke of mercy) <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 7. 10. Here note, <hi>Paul</hi> taryed there ſeauen dayes in all, verſ. 6. That is, he tarryed fiue dayes, and on the ſixt day of his abiding there he preached, and miniſtred the Sacrament, and on the next day departed. ver. 11. Now why is not the publicke meeting with preaching &amp; Sacraments ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring which are Sabbaoth dayes workes performed till
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3348:16"/> the firſt day of the weeke? Why not on any of the former? Why on the laſt of his abiding there? And then laſtly, why is the firſt day of the weeke ſo preciſely mentioned by the holy Ghoſt? Doubtleſſe it vvas the Chriſtian Sabbaoth: elſe all this circumſtance had been in vaine expreſſed and ſet downe. 5. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul.</hi> 1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 16. 1. 2. ordayneth weekly gatherings: but why in diuers Churches? why week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? why the firſt day of the weeke, named againe? why then a worke of mercy? Doubtleſſe all this vvas not in vaine: it was the Chriſtian Sabbaoth. 6. Laſtly, the holy Ghoſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth once againe: to whom? to an inſpired Apoſtle. <hi>Reu.</hi> 1. 10. But why? to enable him vnto a ſanctified work, moſt profitable to the Church, moſt fit for an Apoſtle, and moſt glorious to God: but why vpon this day? and why doth he ſo definitely and ſignificantly tearme this day euen the Lords day? Forſooth, all theſe things are directly fitted to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Sabbaoth: eſtabliſhed by the will and ordinaunce of Chriſt, commaunded and practiſed by the Apoſtles, and continued to the dayes of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Penner of the Reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="60">60 The ſeauenth Reaſon: Drawne from the bare exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Apoſtles, admitting there were no Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for it at all; who being men. 1. peculiarly inſpired with the ſpirit of God. 2. and ſet apart by Chriſt to plant and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh the Church in the new Teſtament: as <hi>Moſes</hi> vvas by God the Father in the olde Teſtament. 3. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were in forty dayes ſpace inſtructed by Chriſt. <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 3. in matter belonging to the Church or kingdome of God; like as <hi>Moſes</hi> was fortie dayes with God vpon the mount, <hi>Deut.</hi> 9. 11. As the Apoſtles therefore muſt needs be praeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to bee as faithfull as <hi>Moſes</hi> in all the houſe of God: ſo could they no more erre in religious matter appertayning or tending to Gods worſhip then <hi>Moſes</hi> did. And therefore as the Apoſtles conſtitutions which are called Commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the Lord, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 28. muſt needs tye the conſcience. So their very practiſe and example in matters religious morall, miniſteriall, directly tending to Gods publicke worſhip and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3348:17"/> ſolemne ſeruice, whoſe reaſon alſo implyeth a contynuance of practiſe (wherein they could nor erre no more then in their conſtitutions and commandements) doth tye the conſcience no leſſe: and ſo we ſee the Apoſtle giueth ſuch direction and command, as if his example were as currant and authenticke as his own perſonall command. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 1. 23. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 17. &amp; 4. 9. Euen as his commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts were of equal force with the commandements of Chriſt. So likewiſe we ſee the argument drawne from exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of inſpired &amp; godly perſons is forcible: as <hi>Io.</hi> 26. 19. <hi>Ma.</hi> 12. 3. 4. 5. Wherfore if the place. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1. 2 were no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement tying or concerning vs, or if the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Commandement of the moral decalogue did not perpetually commaund the keeping holy of a 7. day: Yet the bare exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Apoſtles &amp; their practiſe of keeping holy the firſt day of the weeke, being a morall duty tending to Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the reaſon thereof, implying continuance, dooth tye our conſcience, and is as a neceſſary and ſufficient rule for vs to walk by, to the end of the world.</p>
            <p n="61">61 The eight Reaſon: Is drawne from the circumſtance of time: namely the continuance of it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtles times to our time: Beginning 1. At Chriſt his two-fold apparition on that day: &amp; ſo proceeding. 2. to the holy Ghoſts deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on the Apoſtles on that day. 3. Then to the Apoſtles practiſe at <hi>Troas</hi> on that day: 4. From thence to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthian and Galathian conſtitution and commaund. 5. From thence fortie yeares after &amp; aboue, as the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Codoman. anno Christi.</hi> 55. <hi>&amp;</hi> 93. <hi>Perkins Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia Biblior: anno Chriſti.</hi> 54. <hi>&amp;</hi> 95. Moores Tables <hi>anno:</hi> 55 <hi>&amp;</hi> 97. <hi>Genebr. chronol. anno.</hi> 93 <hi>Baronius. Tom.</hi> 1 <hi>in anno</hi> 53. <hi>&amp;</hi> 97. In the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer yeare they ſay the 1. Epi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtle to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinths was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyps: the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of which time is aboue. 40. yeares.</note> learned iudge) to <hi>Iohn</hi> the inſpired Penner of the Reuelation his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony and mention of that day. 6. Then down into the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean of the Fathers and Councels, witneſſing thereof in their ſeuerall ſucceeding ages Greekes and Latines. <hi>Ignatius, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinus Martyr, Irenaeus, Origen, Tertullian, Baſil, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius, Chryſoſtome, Hierome, Ambroſe, Auguſtine:</hi> and the reſt before cyted. <hi>Theſis,</hi> 15. Togither with the Papiſts teſtimonies for their times, vnto the practiſe of the times wherein vve liue. From vvhence I argue thus: That cuſtome tending to Gods publicke worſhip, hauing ground and warrant of Scripture, which was begun, ordeined and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3348:17"/> practiſed at the firſt by Chriſts inſpired Apoſtles, and was neuer interrupted or intentionally profaned to this howre, by any orthodoxal Church or perſon: but alway confirmed and eſtabliſhed by Chriſtian Magiſtrates, and practiſed by all true Churches and Chriſtians, in all ages from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times to ours; the obſeruation therof muſt needes tie the conſcience (for vvith what conſcience may any Church or perſon break it?) and the queſtioning or breaking of it now, muſt needs proue a ſtrange vnheard nouelty, &amp; head-ſtrong ſingularity, proceeding from a priuate ſpirit. But the former is true of the Chriſtian Sabbaoth. Thereforce the later alſo muſt needs be true.</p>
            <p n="62">62 The ninth argument is drawen from the circumſtance and vniuerſality of place: and cuſtome of the true Churches of Chriſt in all places. It being practiſed; at firſt at Ieruſalem and Troas. 2. Then at Corinth and Galathia. 3. Then in Pathmos (and al Aſia the leſſe as is moſt probable.) 4. Then in the Grecian Churches, as appeareth by the Greek Fathers. 5. Then in the Latine Churches, as appeareth by the Latine Fathers. 6. And laſt of all in all reformed later Churches, both of Lutherane and Orthodoxall iudgement. And no true Chriſtian Church can be named that euer brake off the cuſtome of this day, receaued at the firſt from the Apoſtles. The force of this argument ſtands in this: The Vnity of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, grounded on Gods word, obſerued by Apoſtolicall primitiue orthodoxall &amp; reformed later Churches, in matter tending to Gods publicke ſeruice, doth tye the conſcience. The ſanctifying of the firſt day of the weeke is confirmed by ſuch vnity of cuſtome. Therfore the ſanctifying of the 1. day of the week doth ty the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience. The <hi>Maior</hi> or former pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is proued. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 16. and 14. 33. The <hi>Minor</hi> or aſſumption is already proued. Neither let any man obiect theſe reaſons to be Popiſh which are drawen from cuſtome, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance of time &amp; vniuerſality of place. For ſuch reaſons are moſt forcible, that haue ground of Scripture (which the Papiſts haue not) as neither haue they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance of time, or vniuerſality of place, if ye take away their cracking &amp; facing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3348:18"/> out the matter. And the Fathers rightly thus fight againſt the ſundrie Haeritiques of their times, vvith theſe verie argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p n="63">63 The tenth Argument, is grounded on 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2. Where <hi>Timothy</hi> is commanded to preach the word in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon: the which praecept is perpetuall and appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to all miniſters of the new Teſtament to the end of the world; as that is <hi>Matt.</hi> 28. 19. 20. And that Miniſter, that ſo teacheth not in and out of ſeaſon, directly ſinneth, as brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that commandement of Chriſt and this of the Apoſtle: and incurreth that woe which the ſame Apoſtle denounceth on himſelfe, if hee neglecteth this duty. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 16. Now what is meant in this, for the Miniſter or publicke perſon to teach in ſeaſon, but only to teach in the ſeaſon appointed by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, namely on the publicke day of the Churches and Apoſtles practiſe, and cuſtomable meeting: which being prooued to haue been vſuall on that day, (as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the auncient <hi>Syriacke</hi> tranſlation doth plainly confirm, by adding theſe words vnto the narration of their commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke meeting for receiung of the Lords Supper, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 20. <hi>When ye therefore are gathered together</hi> in die Domini no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri. <hi>On our Lords day.)</hi> It followeth of neceſſity the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter by teaching muſt keepe the Lords day holy, and ſo by conſequence, the people alſo by publicke and ſolemne hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. For there is no publicke teaching can be preſuppoſed without publicke hearing: no more then obedience is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſed without commaund.</p>
            <p n="64">64 The eleuenth Reaſon is concluded from the words of <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 20. The which I can by no meanes ouerſlip; For that I cannot be perſwaded that Ieſus Chriſt our bleſſed Sauiour, and the wiſedome of the Father, did ſpeake in ieſt when as he expreſly &amp; ſeriouſly commanded his hearers &amp; diſciples the Iews, and thoſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lect and ſanctified (for they only haue the gift of inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to pray: <hi>That their flight might not be on the Sabbaoth day;</hi> Speaking of the time of ſacking and euerſion of <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> Now, if it had bin Ceremoniall, and aboliſhed, they needed not haue prayed, but haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3348:18"/> flight on that day, aſwel as any other: without any ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of conſcience at all. Yea, it had beene a ſinne for godly Chriſtian Iewes to haue made a needleſle conſcience of a ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony, fortie yeares after the aboliſhing: eſpecially the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles doctrine of auoyding the obſeruation of Iewiſh daies comming betweene. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 10. 11. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2. 16. 17. And laſt of al, it might ſeem vain in Ieſus Chriſt, and a mockery of his elect: (which were a blaſphemy to ſay) to command them to pray againſt the breaking of a Sabbaoth day, if it were abrogated long before, both <hi>quo ad genus &amp; ſpeciem;</hi> that is both in reſpect of the ſpeciall day (the which the Iewes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued) and alſo in reſpect of the morall of the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement (that is an holy obſeruation of a ſeauenth day vnto God). Now the ſpeciall day which the Iewe obſerued was ceremoniall, and doubtleſſe abrogated. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 16. 17. But the <hi>genus</hi> or morall of the fourth Commaundement, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly was not aboliſhed. For <hi>Iohn</hi> the writer of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation (euen after the ſacking &amp; ouerthrow of <hi>Hieruſalem)</hi> brings in the ſolemn mention of the Chriſtian Sabbaoth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the title of the Lords day, as a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> name receiued ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally &amp; ſo tearmed by the Church by a note of excellence, as peculiarly dedicated to the honour and ſeruice of God in Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="65">65 The twelfth Reaſon: Is drawne from the effectes of the wiſedome of the fleſh, and ſpirit; and thus is framed. 1. That ordinance tending to Gods publike worſhip and glory, and mans inſtruction and building vp in godlineſſe and knowledge: The which is grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded on Gods holy word, and practiſe of the holy and inſpired Apoſtles: The vvhich is liked of, approued of, and gladly practiſed with great ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall comfort and profit, by the moſt godly, vertuous, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and ſincere godly learned writers, Teachers and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Gods truth: muſt needes be according to the vvill and ordinaunce of God. Such is the ordinance of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Sabbaoth. Therefore it is according to the will and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce of God. The propoſition is grounded on 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 11. 15. &amp; 14. 32. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 11. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. 43.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3348:19"/> 
               <hi>Io.</hi> 5. 20. <hi>Io.</hi> 7. 17. The aſſumption is confirmed on the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and truth of ſuch effectes in all the godly of all places, and times, ſince the Apoſtles to our times. And the ſerious and iudiciall Conſiderer ſhall obſerue them, both Miniſters and people among us in this Land, (to go no further) to be the moſt religious, zealous, conſcionable, and faithfull Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and moſt of all profiting and growing in all grace and knowledge, that with conſcience, delight, and diligence doe effectually ſanctify the Lords day. 2. Again, That ordinance tending to Gods publicke ſeruice and glory, and mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and building vp in godlineſſe, and is grounded on Gods word: the which is diſliked, diſputed againſt, cauil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at, withſtood, broken and profaned by the moſt carnall, vngodly, irreligious, corrupt and vaine perſons: muſt needs be moſt agreeing to the wiſdome &amp; will of God. Such is the ordinaunce of the holy obſeruation of the Lords day. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is moſt agreeing to the wiſdome and will of God. The <hi>Maior</hi> or firſt propoſition is grounded on 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 18. and 2. 14. and 3. 19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 11. <hi>Io.</hi> 3. 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 5. 7. The aſſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or <hi>Minor</hi> is grounded on <hi>Pſa.</hi> 92. 1. 2. 6. and confirmed by experience. For he that ſhall vnpartially obſerue this truth, ſhall finde that the Sabbaoth euery where is onely diſliked, withſtood, diſgraced, diſputed againſt, rayled at, ſcorned &amp; profaned, by the moſt profane, carnal, couetous, Atheiſts, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines, men of no conſcience, holineſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or truth in them: and ſuch as eyther liue in vnlawfull callings, or vnlawfully in their honeſt callings: ſuch as fidlers, ſtage-players, beare and bull-baiters, gameſters, drunkards, vſurers, papiſts, fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of loue, theeues, vagrantrogues, (wearers, oppreſſors, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeners, Epicures, and voluptuous liuers. 3. Againe: That doctrine practiſe and perſwaſion the vvhich is grounded in the Scripture, and is moſt agreeable to godlines, peace of a good conſcience, and fits a Chriſtian beſt to appeare with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of hart &amp; ioy before the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeate of Chriſt: that doctrine &amp; perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt needs be more agreeable to Gods wil then contrary: ſuch is the doctrine practiſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of keeping holy the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sabbaoth or Lords day:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3348:19"/> therfore the keeping holy of the lords day, togither with the doctrine and perſwaſion of the ſame is moſt agreeable to the will of God. 4. And laſt of all, that doctrine practiſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion differing from the practiſe of the Apoſtles and all Apoſtolicall Churches and teachers, yea from the doctrine &amp; practiſe of the Church wherin they liue, the which is moſt agreeable to the will of man, the wiſdome of the fleſhe, the manners of the wicked, the ſtate of ignorance and ſinne, and of an euill conſcience, the hindrance of the Goſpell, the the breach of all good Diſcipline, and order in the Church, and the very high way to Atheiſme, carnall liberty, and all impious licentiouſneſſe and confuſion; and ſo by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence procuring and increaſing the wrath and iudgement of God: or euen but tending therunto, or any part therof, is impious and vngodly. Such is the iudgement and practiſe of the deniers or diſgracers, or oppoſite diſputers, or omitters or profaneners of the Lords day: and of thoſe alſo that teach a liberty of breaking or omitting of the Lords day. Therfore ſuch iudgement, practiſe or perſwaſion is impious &amp; wicked, <hi>And ſo much of the ſecond Quaeſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="66">66 The third Quaeſtion and the laſt, concerning this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie of the Chriſtian Sabbaoth, is this: <hi>VVhether the Church of GOD might haue choſen at the firſt another day, or hath yet authority or Chriſtian libertie to abrogate or alter the Lords day into any other certaine or vncertaine day; or whether it be not of neceſſity to be obſerued to the end of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="67">67 This Quaeſtion becauſe it dependeth on the former: therfore the affirmation and proofe of the former prooueth alſo the negation of the former part hereof, and the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the later: the which I therfore will the more briefely handle as a point ſufficiently confirmed.</p>
            <p n="68">68 The firſt Reaſon: The Church hath no Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to alter any day the which hath abſolute Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Word. The Chriſtian Sabbaoth or Lords day hath abſolute Commaundement in the Word: as alreadie hath been proued. Therefore the Church hath no Chriſtian liberty to alter the Lords day into any other.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:3348:20"/>
            <p n="69"> 69 The ſecond Reaſon: The Church could neuer alter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of the Morall law, or of the lawe of Nature: nor can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alter the morall ordinances and conſtitutions of the inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Apoſtles. The obſeruation or keeping holy of one day of euery ſeauen, is of the Morall lawe and law of Nature; and beſides, the keeping holy of the firſt day of the weeke is a conſtitution and commaundement of the inſpired Apoſtles. Therefore the Church coulde not nor cannot alter the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping holy of one day of ſeauen vnto God: nor the keeping holy of the firſt day of the weeke to Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="70">70 The third Reaſon: whatſoeuer Chriſt aſcribeth as his owne and proper to himſelfe, no Church or Chriſtian ought or may aſcribe vnto themſelues: But Chriſt aſcribeth as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to himſelfe, that he is the Lord of the Sabbaoth: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, no church or perſon may aſcribe the Sabbaoth of Chriſt to himſelfe: and ſo by conſequence may not profane nor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Lords day into any other.</p>
            <p n="71">71 The fourth Reaſon. By whatſoeuer onely power the Iewiſh Sabbaoth was abrogated, &amp; the Chriſtian Sabbaoth inſtituted; by the ſame power and none other can it be abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated againe. But by the only power of Chriſt his <hi>Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum eſt</hi> or ſacrifice, was the Iewiſh Sabbaoth abrogated, and by vertue of his reſurrection the Lords day originally inſtituted, and by Apoſtolicall power and authority the one relinquiſhed, and the other practiced. Therefore by the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly power of Chriſt and his Apoſtles and by none other can the Lords day be aboliſhed againe.</p>
            <p n="72">72 The fift Reaſon. If there cannot come ſo long as the world laſteth ſo great a cauſe of changing the Lords day as the Apoſtles had of ordaining it; Then the Church cannot aboliſh the Lords day to the end of the world. But ſo great cauſe of aboliſhing the Lords day, the Church can neuer haue, as the Apoſtles had of ordayning: namely the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and reſt of Chriſt. Therefore the Church cannot abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the Lords day to the end of the world.</p>
            <p n="73">73 The ſixth and laſt Reaſon. If the Church haue no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aucthority then by the word of God either in generall or
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3348:20"/> ſpeciall to appoint or alter any thing eſtabliſhed, then the Church can neuer alter the Lords day, nor appoint any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſteade thereof. But the former is true; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo the later. For there is no ſhadowe of authority or ground eyther generall or ſpeciall in the word, touching the alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Lords day or appointing of any other in the ſteade thereof. And finally, vnleſſe the Church hath the ſame infallible warrant to bee led into all truth as the inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Apoſtles had (which the Papiſts falſly affirme; but wee conſtantly deny) the Church can neuer haue equall power in aboliſhing the obſeruation of the firſt day of the weeke as the Apoſtles had in ordayning: and ſo by conſequence can it neuer be lawfully accompliſhed, for want of due power to performe the ſame. So that it followeth by ineuitable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that the keeping holy of the Lords day, or firſt day of the weeke, muſt vnremoouedly ſtand vnto the end of the World. And ſo an end of this third and laſt queſtion.</p>
            <p n="74">74 Now touching the obiections that are alleaged againſt the keeping holy of the Lords day; they are of ſundry ſorts, as are the various apprehenſions and opinions of men erring on the right and left hand of the truth. The which their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering cauillations albeit it were not quite amiſſe to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed on either ſide: yet I haue thought it fitter at this time to let them paſſe, leaſt the Reader might be rather tyred then inſtructed: the rather becauſe the moſt of them in very deed are but of froathy &amp; feeble nature, and are not able to ſtand or to maintaine themſelues; the day reuealing them to bee but falſe, and the fire but ſtubble, being grounded on an euill conſcience, maintained by more ſubtilty then truth or art, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by ſundry others, and are aboundantly confuted by the former reaſons. Only I purpoſe to take notice and giue anſwere vnto the cauillations of our preſent times, vvhich beare the greateſt ſhewe both againſt the things alleaged for the truth, as alſo for eſtabliſhment of their owne errour.</p>
            <p n="75">75 Againſt the places of Scripture alleaged for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Sabbaoth; They ſay that the reaſons drawn from <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 7. &amp; 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 2. make nothing for the confirmation of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3348:21"/> the Lords day. For that the Greeke word ſoundeth in both places <hi>one of the Sabbaoths:</hi> which being literally vnderſtood muſt needs haue reference to the Iewes Sabbaoth, not to the firſt day of the weeke which is our Lords daie. To vvhich obiection firſt I oppoſe the maine ſtreame of all Interpreters that euer vvere both olde and newe, that vnderſtand them for the firſt day of the vveeke, and doe ſo tranſlate them. Secondly, I ſay it is an Hebraiſme or Hebrewe kinde of ſpeech vſuall in the Scriptures to ſet downe One inſteade of the firſt: as <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 1. <hi>Mark</hi> 16 9. <hi>Luke,</hi> 24. 1. <hi>Io,</hi> 20. 1. And the word Sabbaoth for a <hi>Weeke.</hi> As <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> 25. 8. <hi>Luke,</hi> 18. 12. (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.) And thus doe <hi>Caluin, Martyr, Beza. B B. Hooper:</hi> and euen the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Papiſts: <hi>Eraſmus, Ianſenius, Bellarmine, Emanuel Sa:</hi> and ſundry others, obſerue vpon theſe places. And further for the place of the 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 16. 2. It is very euident out of the Fathers, <hi>Iuſtinus, Tertullian,</hi> and others, that from the ordinance of the Apoſtles grounded on this place, the primitiue times did make collections for the poore on this very day vvhich vvas the firſt day of the vveeke celebrated by them to the honour of Chriſt his reſurrection and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique vvorſhip of God; as <hi>Zanchius</hi> that moſt learned and iudiciall Diuine doth ſoundly conclude. Beſides, ther want not ancient manuſcripts to make this place more manifeſt by adding <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Text: as <hi>Beza</hi> noteth, and <hi>Cryſpine</hi> in his greeke Teſtament together vvith <hi>Wechelus</hi> in his edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Septuaginta</hi> doe expreſſe. Touching the place of <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1. 10. vvhich maketh cleere mention of the Lords day; the obſeruation whereof is ſeconded by the Primitiue Fathers and Churches immediatly ſucceeding the writer of that book: they haue nothing to alleage, but that they holde it doubtfull whether that book be Canonicall or not. Which cauill albeit it bee vnanſwerably confuted by <hi>Beza</hi> and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry others: yet I iudge it ſitter to be decided by a cudgell of the Magiſtrates owne faggot, (or the hatchet rather) then to be notized or vouchſafed the peaceable or quiet anſwere of ſober men; for that it muſt needs be an opinion of inſolent
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3348:21"/> and palpable lewdneſſe, that cannot ſtand but by calling the vndoubted Scriptures of canonical authority, and principles of the Chriſtian faith in quaeſtion.</p>
            <p n="76">76 For the confirmation of their moſt weake and bad o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they brokenly alleage certaine Scriptures, from which they draw euen by the eares againſt their wils three ſeuerall concluſions. The firſt concluſion is this: <hi>The fourth Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement is meerely Ceremoniall, and therfore vtterly aboliſhed and is Iewiſh to obſerue.</hi> To this I ſay in generall it croſſeth all mens iudgemens that euer were of any note as in parte appeareth <hi>Theſe.</hi> 20. and therfore is actually abſurde and a very Nouel, and is beſides the doore to Atheiſme, carnall liberty and all profaneneſſe, a manifeſt diſabling of the other 9. Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements &amp; occaſion of neglect giuen to them eſpecially that care for none. For further anſwere to this bare Aſſertion, Look <hi>Theſ.</hi> 45. 46. 47. 48. 49. 50. But for the Scriptures they alleage for the ground of this their Concluſion as <hi>Exodus,</hi> 31. 13. 16. and 35. 2. <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> 20. 12: They are too ſhort for their poſition; for theſe places prooue the Iewiſh Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth to haue in it ſomething ceremoniall, tranſitory, and as the ſhadowe aboliſhed by Chriſt the ſubſtance, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2. 16. 17. in that parte wherein it was ceremoniall, which was meerly proper to the Iewe: but by this they diſproue not the Sabbaoth dayes politicall reſpecte of reſt of the bodies of ourſelues, our ſeruants and our Cattell, <hi>Exodus,</hi> 20. 17. with <hi>Deu.</hi> 5. 14. and morall part therof; which is the publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God. <hi>Exo.</hi> 20. 9. 10. which are perpetually to remain as the other laws of like equity &amp; nature, being eſpecially by Chriſt confirmed and by his Apoſtles and Primitiue Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches continued, and by vs therefore to bee practiſed to the Worlds end. VVherefore the ſtricte obſeruation alſo of a holy reſt or Sabbaoth vnto God in the new Teſtament is not a Iewiſh thing. For ſeeing the Iewe did reſt by a mixt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iunius de polit: Moſis: cap.</hi> 8.</note> partly morall, partly politicall, and partly ceremoniall; We reſt in no ſenſe for the later but the former two. Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly firſt for the Morall and then for the politicall reſpect: which ſeeing they are commaunded vs as ſtrictly; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3348:22"/> vs at neerely as they did the Iewes; wee ought with no leſſe conſcience to obſerue them then the Iews. And ſeeing the actions of men are really diſtinguiſhed by their ends for which they are done; and wee propoſing not the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall or end proper to the Iewe, but onely the Morall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to vs vvith them: our ſtricte obſeruing of the Lords day cannot bee counted Iewiſh, though hereby alſo wee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the verie gathering of any ſticke or kindling of anie fire that ſhall hinder the ſeruice of GOD in our ſelues or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p n="77">77 The ſecond Concluſion that they frame is this: <hi>All dayes are alike,</hi> no difference in the Goſpell by the word of God, and are diſtinguiſhed only by the Magiſtrates, not by Gods commaund. Nay farther (except the Magiſtrate en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne) it were a ſinne to obſerue religiouſly any dayes for the ſolemne ſeruice of God aboue others. The proofes heereof are <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 10. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 16. 17. The former of the which, namely, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 6. argueth our Chriſtian liberty, in reſpecting all dayes alike which are not diſcerned (ſay theſe men) by the commandement of a Magiſtrate: of the Church ſay the Rhemiſtes: but of neither ſayth Maſter <hi>Fulke,</hi> but of the commaundement of God only: and ſo is this place ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently anſwered. Maſter <hi>Greenham</hi> (a man of reuerend me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie) anſwereth this obiection, by affirming him the vvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker Chriſtian that counteth all dayes alike. V. 5. for that hee muſt needes be weake in Chriſtianity that eſteemeth all daies alike notwithſtanding the plain conſtitution and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the inſpired Apoſtles going before. The auncient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Origen, Ambroſe, Oecumenius Primaſius, Anſelmus,</hi> do vnderſtand the Apoſtle to ſpeake of faſting from meates on certaine dayes, and (as <hi>Chryſoſtome, Theodoret</hi> and <hi>Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact</hi> define it) from ſwines fleſhe: which dayes and abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence ſay <hi>Caluin, Bullinger, Beza, Oleuian, Piſcator, Eraſmus, Lyra,</hi> and the very Rhemiſts, are to be conſtrued of the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies meerely Iewiſh and ceremoniall: with the which ſenſe this Scripture being limited, it includeth not the dayes eſtabliſhed and practiſed in the new Teſtament by Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3348:22"/> authority. The other places of <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 10. &amp; <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 16. 17. are by all Interpreters alſo vnderſtood of the Iewiſh feſtiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſo farre forth only as they were Ceremonials, figures and ſhadowes of things to come, and being aboliſhed by Chriſt his comming ought not to be obſerued any longer. And this, the very ſcope of the Apoſtle, circumſtances of the places, and manner of ſpeaking and noting the names of the dayes and times and that in the plurall number, aboundantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme. And thus doth <hi>Caluin, Beza, Marlorat, Zanchius, Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator, Lyra, Eraſmus,</hi> the Papiſt <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Rhemiſts,</hi> and (before them) all the ſtreame of Graecian Fathers with <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> interpret both theſe Scriptures; ſo that (as <hi>Zanchius</hi> ſpeakes) <hi>The Apoſtle in theſe places doth not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that there ſhould bee any certaine dayes publikely ſolemnized in the Church, wherin the faithfull might aſſemble to pray and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Sacraments together. For the Apoſtles and other the godly did vſually come togither on the Lords day, and would that al things ſhould be done by order in the Church. Wherfore</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>vnleſſe we would affirme that the Apoſtle did contradict himſelfe, it muſt needes be confeſſed that the Apoſtle in theſe places to the</hi> Gal. <hi>&amp;</hi> Col. <hi>did nothing leſſe then teach that no dayes ſhould be ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerued in the Church of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="78">78 The third Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion ſoundeth thus: <hi>Euery day is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall Sabbaoth in Chriſt his Kingdome: and that is a reſt from ſinne and a continuall ſeruing of God. So farre ſhould we be, of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing one day aboue another.</hi> The places of their proofe are <hi>Eſay,</hi> 66. 23. and 56. 1. 2. and 58. 13. 14. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4. 6. 7. 8 9. 10. But here hence they conclude iuſt nothing to the point. For the firſt place; <hi>Caluin, Bucholcher,</hi> and others interpret it of the eternall reſt in heauen; or if we take it for the Chriſtian Sabbaoth (as <hi>Chemnitius</hi> and others do) why may we not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, as alſo <hi>Eſay,</hi> 56. 2. 4. 6. 7. both for a prophecy &amp; preſcription of the Gentiles ſanctifying of the Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth in the new Teſtament, ſeeing the Prophet (ſpecially in the later place) ſpeakes euidently of the Church of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles which muſt needes bee in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? The ſecond and third places doe affirme thus much,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3348:23"/> that we ought not to commit any ſinne vpon the Sabbaoth. What then? will they therfore conclude we ought not to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue any certaine Sabbaoth day? it were too abſurd. Now the laſt place teacheth that Chriſtians ought to reſt from the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> own works, that is from ſin and diſobedience, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally: but what hinders this the Chriſtian Sabbaoth or ſettled proportion of time of the publicke worſhip of God, by the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring of the word, by prayer and receiuing of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Nay by theſe collections either we muſt haue no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſolemne dayes at all: And then (ſayth <hi>Caluine) Praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſima impendet Eccleſiae perturbatio &amp; ruina.</hi> A moſt praeſent <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſtit. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 8. §. 32.</note> ruine and confuſion will come vnto the Church: Or elſe in the other extreamity wee muſt do nothing elſe euery day, then meete together publikely, and without intermiſſion continually to heare, to pray, to take the Sacraments. And then what ſhall become of the Common-wealth and houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, the Magiſtrate and Maſter, the ſubiect and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant? how ſhall the one rule, or the other obey and ſerue? what vſe of our daily callings? who ſhall prouide for our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies whiles we (worſe then Inſidels) caſt off the care there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? how ſhall wee cloath and feede our bodies? or what vſe ſhall there bee of thoſe Commaundements of GOD, vvhich were giuen before the Law; <hi>In the ſweat of thy browes thou ſhalt eate thy breade?</hi> Or in the Law. <hi>Sixe daies thou ſhalt labour.</hi> Or in the Goſpell. <hi>We commaund them to worke with quietneſſe, and to eate their owne breade?</hi> So that this fancie d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es men eyther into one extreamity of Atheiſme, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and ſanctifie no publicke dayes at all; or of <hi>Iudaiſme,</hi> to Sabbatize all dayes in the ſuperlatiue degree. Other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions there are hammered out of other Scriptures: as namely, <hi>Marke,</hi> 2. 7. <hi>The Sabbaoth was made for man:</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore man may vſe it or not vſe it at his pleaſure; as though Baptiſme or the Lords Supper, the miniſtry and preaching of the Word, and other ordinaunces of God, were not made for m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> (if they were) as if man might vſe them at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ine, <hi>Matthew,</hi> 12. 8. <hi>Chriſt is the Lord of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth;</hi> and therfore as Lord might abrogate the Sabbaoth,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3348:23"/> and admit this to be true, yet neither doth it proue that he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Ceremoniall; neither diſproue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut that he eſtabliſhed the Moral part of the Sabbaoth for euer. But I am aſhamed of the ſeelineſſe of theſe obiections: enough to make a man perſwaded that ſome enemy of theirs ſhould fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them vpon them to abuſe them; ſaue that the maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of ſuch opinion may iuſtly ſeeme to bee but men vnſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. Wherfore vntill I ſee reaſons more forcible then theſe, confirming a more probable opinion then this, I will leaue both reaſons and opinion as I finde them, and in the meane time will be bold to ſay; <hi>Such as the weake foundation is, ſuch is the building.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus <hi>(O Reader)</hi> according to the modell of my prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtrength, thou haſt the truth of the Chriſtian Sabbaoth propoſed and confirmed to thy conſcience: A doctrine harmeleſſe, true, and holy, making thee holy and praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thee to heauen, agreeing to the Scripture, to right rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to common ciuility, and euen to ciuill policies. A doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine conforming vs to the Commandement of God, yea euen to his bleſſed and holy Image. A doctrine bringing much glory vnto God, and benefit to man, knowledge to the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ſenſe vnto the hardned, direction to the willing, diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline to the irregular, conſcience to the obſtinate, comfort to the conſcienced, and bringing none inconuenience in the world. A doctrine that addeth face, faſhion, growth and fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitude vnto a Church, ſtrength and comely order to a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; giuing propagation vnto the Goſpell, helpe and vigor to the lawes: eaſe, honor, and obedience vnto the Gouernors: vnity and quiet to the people: and laſtly, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine happineſſe and bleſſing to them all. For the which doctrine whoſoeuer argues, pleadeth for GOD, for his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for his worſhip, for his Commaundement and will, for his Word, his Sacraments, and inuocation: for the Lawe, for the Goſpell, for <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets, for CHRIST and his Apoſtles, for the vpholding and flouriſhing eſtate of the Church and Common-wealth, of Schooles and Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities, and of the faithfull Miniſtrie of Chriſt. In a word
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3348:24"/> they pleade for the wearied bodies reſt, for the euill conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence quiet; for the ſound practiſe of godlineſſe and mercy, in a certaine, ſettled, and conſtant order. And ſo by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence for heauen it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The contrary iudgement worketh contrary effectes. For it depriueth GOD of his honour, the Church of Religion, the Common wealth of order, the body of reſt, the ſoule of inſtruction, the life of direction, the word of attendance, the miniſtery of reuerence, and drawes along a world of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences and miſchiefes beſides. For it plainely bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſlouth and ſcandall in the Miniſtry: neglect &amp; meere contempt of Miniſtry in the people; confirming blindneſſe and ſuperſtition in the ignorant, quenching the zeale of the more forward: ſtrengthening the hands of the more wicked, and giuing liberty to them that are too apt to take it of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning of the Sabbaoth day of God. It hinders the courſe of the Goſpell, depriueth of the meanes of godlineſſe, it defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the beauty, &amp; cuts in two the very ſinews of the Church, enlarging Sathans horrid kingdome and power of darknes, by giuing ſtrength to Athiſme, Papiſme, and carnall goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; Aboliſhing the Vniuerſities by ineuitable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and ſhaking the frame and fabricke, yea poyſoning vp the vitall powers of the very Common-wealth: And in a word drawing on confuſion, irreligion, Barbariſme, Gods curſe and vtter deſolation on them all.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the truth of this doctrine of the Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth being cleere: it followeth that all aduerſarie iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to it are condemned: whether they bee <hi>Swinckefeldians,</hi> that wil haue no miniſtry: or Familiſts and their fellow Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts that wil haue no Sabbaoth, or Iewes that inſiſt vpon the Legall Sabbaoth, or Papiſts that hold the Sabbaoth ſanctified by their impious Maſſe and other Antichriſtian I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatries and will-worſhips; or Libertines that giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues &amp; others liberty to labour on the Sabbaoth, or to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane it by vaine ſports, games, recreations, feaſtinges, daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings, Maypoles, Church-ales, ſtage-playes, and the like, more then heatheniſh vanities, or whatſoeuer may be called
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3348:24"/> the will or wayes of man, or whatſoeuer tendeth to profane or hinder the effectuall ſanctifying of the Chriſtian Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth: whoſe ſeuerall obliquities, (being oppoſite to al ſound iudgements and Chriſtian practiſe) ſufficiently manifeſt the falſhood of themſelues, and mutually confute each other, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compared with the truth of God.</p>
            <p>It remaineth that thou bee exhorted (O Chriſtian peruſet of this truth of God) vnto the conſcionable &amp; carefull prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Chriſtian Sabbaoth. Conſider vvith thy ſelfe the reaſons that haue been alleaged; and let the euidence of them cauſe thee to captiuate thy thoughts vnto them. And know, that if among them all but one bee true, it is enough; one is too much for a Chriſtian man to depraue or cauell at, who beleeueth a Iudgement day to come: I doubt not but a man might more eaſily perſwade the multitude to any extreamity then to the right, and ſo to break the Sabbaoth then to keep it holy: corrupted doctrines are familiar to corrupted nature. And it is not hard to perſwade vnto that liberty, which all men pleade for and purſue. Nay more, it is not poſſible for any man to teach that liberty which the moſt part wil not far exceede in practiſe. So vnſeaſonable are the doctrines of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſlacke the reines of godlineſſe vnto this head ſtrong and vnruly age of ours: and ſo vnſound; againſt the which all ſound and learned iudgements, and godly Churches &amp; pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons practiſe, are oppoſitely ſet. And therfore if the Apoſtles and all faithfull teachers and ſeruants of God haue walked in this path before, wherin they paſſed through and from this world, without either outwarde inconuenience, or inwarde wound of conſcience; but with much ſpirituall profit and ſenſible increaſe of knowledge and of grace, and with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall, finall, and vnſpeakeable peace and comfort: who will not hazard the imitation of their practiſe for the gayning of like benefite? Or who, that hath not ſet his conſcience and common ſenſe to ſale, will leaue the certaine way of all the Saints and ſeeke a newe found way, which no man euer went to gaine the bleſſings they enioyed? For, did they enioy ſo great benefits by ſanctifying this day, and doeſt thou think
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3348:25"/> to get them by profaning it? My iudgement is, he that will haue a way of his owne finding, it were fit hee enioyed a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of his owne making. But (O Chriſtian Reader) if euer thou wilt ſanctifie thine euerlaſting Sabbaoth in heauen, Learne then effectually to ſanctifie it vpon earth, according to the Commaundement and wil of God: which if the more wilfull will not do, who walke in the wide way of the greater part of men, yet Chriſt ſhall not want to ſanctifie a day vnto himſelfe; It ſhall be done in deſpight of them, without them: and they ſhall melt away in leauing of the truth they ſawe, and winked at. And albeit the Phariſees do ſtill deſpiſe the counſell of God againſt themſelues, and ſome peruerſe ones will be euer carping and corroding of this truth, yet <hi>Wiſedome will be iuſtified of all her children.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>GAL. 6. 16.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As many as walke according to this rule; peace ſhall be vpon them and mercy, and vpon the Iſraell of God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3348:25"/>
            <head>The Practiſe of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Sabbaoth, according to the</hi> WORD.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Practiſe of the Chriſtian Sabbaoth ſtandeth eyther in
<list>
                     <item>1. Praeparation to it:</item>
                     <item>2. Sanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of it.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>Praeparation,</hi> is a fitting of our ſelues before hand, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the duties of the Sabbaoth according to Gods wil: vvhich dutie the Church of God among the Iewes did moſt carefully vſe and practiſe, the day before the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth. <hi>Mark.</hi> 15. 42. <hi>Luk.</hi> 23. 54. A duty needefull in reſpect of 1. The glorious praeſence of God in whoſe ſight we are, and before whom we are more ſpecially to praeſent our ſelues the next day. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1. 12. <hi>Habac.</hi> 1. 13. 2. In reſpect of the holineſſe and purity that is required of vs in vſing the ſacred ordinaunces of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 93. 5. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 16. 17. <hi>Mich.</hi> 6. 6. 8. 3. And laſtly in reſpect of the vanity &amp; profaneneſſe of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and thereby our vnfitneſſe to vſe Gods ordinances. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 15. 18. 19. 23. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4. 17.
<list>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:3348:26"/>
                     <item> The duties of praeparation are eyther
<list>
                           <item>1. Speciall and proper to that day:
<list>
                                 <item>1. In obſeruing the due time of the Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth, which doubtleſſe is one whole naturall day: as appeares, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 10. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 23. 32. which time beginneth at the euening before the day <hi>(which is the time of praeparation)</hi> and endeth alſo on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth euen (the time appointed by God of naturall reſt.) <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13. 19. with <hi>Leuit.</hi> 23. 32.</item>
                                 <item>2. In remoouing all things that may hinder the ſanctifying of it the next day, both in our ſelues &amp; in our ſeruants: and this we are to preuent with ſpeciall care and prouidence: both to keepe the peace and quiet of our conſcience in preuenting of a ſin, cauſing vs to profane the Sabbaoth: as alſo thereby to redeeme our ſpirituall profit, and to cut away occaſion of offence and euill example vnto others, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 23.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. Common to other dayes, and therefore now eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially required: and they are,
<list>
                                 <item>1. Examining our conſciences: and repentance. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 59.</item>
                                 <item>2. Reading, and Meditation of Gods word. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. 2. &amp; 119. 97. <hi>Ioſu.</hi> 1. 8. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 6. 8. 9. &amp; 11. 19. <hi>Io.</hi> 5. 35. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16.</item>
                                 <item>3. Inſtruction, examining and praeparing of our Families, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 7. and 11. 18. 20. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 18. 19. <hi>Ioſu.</hi> 24. 15.</item>
                                 <item>4. Prayer, inuocation, confeſſion, petition, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion and praiſe, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 17. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 17. 18.</item>
                                 <item>5. Singing of Pſalmes. <hi>Iam.</hi> 5. 13. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 19.</item>
                                 <item>6. Sobriety of dyet and going to bed in due time: that our bodies be not diſquieted, or diſtempered, and made vnfit and vnpraepared to the duties of the Sabbaoth. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. 8. <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. 34.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>II. <hi>Sanctification,</hi> of the Sabbaoth day it ſelfe: the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3348:26"/> whereof God biddeth vs, <hi>Remember,</hi> becauſe we eaſily forget the beſt and moſt needefull duties. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in euery perſon is to obſerue his duty required. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting or neglecting whereof is to bee accounted vnto God. And the perſons are</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>I. The Magiſtrate, or Perſon hauing authority; either the
<list>
                     <item>1. Greater: of the Common-wealth: whoſoeuer hath publicke lawfull power to commaunde or ouer-rule, more or leſſe. The greater Magiſtrate is called to bee a nurſing Father of the Church of God, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49. 23. And therfore herein muſt he look and remember that the Church be fed, and not deliuered ouer to dry Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that ſtatue their children. They are Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Miniſters, and their power is of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. 2. 6. For elſe they could doe nothing. <hi>Io.</hi> 19. 11. This they muſt acknowledge and therefore honour God, and vphold his ordinances aboue all things, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the penalty of a heauy woe. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 30. their due is limited. <hi>Matt.</hi> 22. 21. They muſt therefore giue to God his due: elſe they muſt know that God can abaſe them that walke in pride, in whoſe eyes they are as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. 32. 34. They are alſo called gods in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte of that Image to which they ought to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and muſt feare God. <hi>Exodus,</hi> 18. 2. Elſe they ſhall dye like men: <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 82. 6. 7. Laſtly, they are to know that by Chriſt kings reigne. <hi>Prou.</hi> 8. 15. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt employ their power &amp; authority to the ſeruice and glory of Chriſt; and ſo to kiſſe the Sonne of God: and that alſo vnder paine, leaſt Chriſt be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and hee breake them in pieces like a Potters veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 11. 12. 9. Wherefore ſeeing Chriſt is now Lord of the Sabbaoth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 8. they muſt take eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall care not to vſurpe the right of Chriſt, but ſerue the Lord in feare, and remember to keepe holy the Chriſtian Sabbaoth; whereof they haue cleare and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Commandement, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28. 9. 10. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 46. 2. 4. 10. Becauſe the kingdome is our Lords &amp; his Chriſts.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3348:27"/> Who is the King of kings, and Lord of lords. <hi>Reu.</hi> 11. 15. &amp; 17. 14. &amp; 19. 6. 16. The duty of the Magiſtrate of the Common-wealth, is
<list>
                           <item>1. To repreſſe the profaning of the Sabbaoth: for, <hi>Qui non prohibet cùm poteſt, iubet. Leu.</hi> 19. 17. This duty ſtandeth in vſing all meanes wherby the profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Sabbaoth is repreſſed: Namely, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. 15. reproue, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. 17. 18. threaten, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. 21. hinder: <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. 19. 22. and puniſh the profaning of it. <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. 20.</item>
                           <item>2. To commaund and compell it to be ſanctified. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 34. 33. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 10. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 24. 15.</item>
                           <item>3. To ſanctifie it himſelf, his children, Nobles, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants and whole Court, both priuately. <hi>Pſal,</hi> 5. 7. <hi>Acts.</hi> 10. 1. 2. As alſo publikely. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 46. 2. 4. 10. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 11. 5. 7. 9. The duties of priuate &amp; publicke ſanctifying, Look furder in the duties of the people: to which the Prince and other Magiſtrate is no leſſe ſtrictly tyed, then the meaneſt of his ſubiects or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The Leſſer: as euery houſholder ouer his family: who alſo may bee called a leſſe Magiſtrate, as man is called a leſſer world; In reſpecte of the authority he hath to commaund. <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 1. 5. alſo of the dutie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 19. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. 6. 7. and laſtly of the account that he muſt make to God; <hi>Col.</hi> 3 25. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 8. 9. 10. The ſpeciall duties of the Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder are:
<list>
                           <item>1. To ſanctifie it and keepe it holy himſelfe, with all care and conſcience. <hi>Ex.</hi> 20. 10. <hi>Thou—Remember.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. To commaund and compell his family hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that they may effectually practiſe it as wel as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>Gen,</hi> 18. 19. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 24. 15. <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4. 16. <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 1. 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. 6. 7. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 10. <hi>Thy Sonne, thy Daughter, thy man and maide-ſeruant. Remember.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3 To cauſe the very Stranger and beaſt to reſt: <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 10. <hi>Prou.</hi> 12. 10.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:3348:27"/>
               <item> II. The Miniſter of God, or Teacher of Gods word; who is Gods ſteward: and therfore is required to be 1. wiſe &amp;. 2. faithful, to rule &amp; giue them their portion of meat in ſeaſon <hi>(in the ſeaſon appointed of God: Remember thou keep holy the Sabbaoth day.) Luk.</hi> 12. 42. He is giuen of God vnto his Church for the gathering of the Saints, for the worke of the Miniſtry, &amp; building vp of Gods Church (to which purpoſe, the Sabbaoth was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.) <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 11. 12. 13. He is commanded to preach. 1. in ſeaſon <hi>(of Gods Sabbaoth)</hi> 2. and out of ſeaſon (at all ſit times and iuſt occaſions)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2. Therfore he is effectually alſo &amp; principally to ſanctifie the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Sabbaoth aboue al others; ſeeing it is a good thing on the Sabbaoth to declare the works &amp; word of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92. 1. 2. 4. 5. And he the publick perſon appointed to be the publicke declarer of Gods word and workes, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 3. 17. He muſt therefore ſanctifie the Sabbaoth day, ſeeing he is the Agent and Miniſter of Chriſt, and the diſpoſer of the ſecrets of God: and therefore he is eſpecially appointed to be faithfull, and that vnder a fearefull woe and penaltie. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 16. <hi>Matt.</hi> 24. 51. <hi>Luke,</hi> 12. 47. 48. He muſt I ſay ſanctifie the Sabbaoth; and that by the word of God and prayer, vvhich are the meanes of ſanctifying euery creature of God. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 5. Of the which ſanctifying hee hath a ſpeciall charge. <hi>Ezechi.</hi> 44. 23. 24. and the contrary whereof is a moſt grieuous and expreſſed ſinne. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22. 26. The duties of the Miniſter, vpon the Chriſtian Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth, are theſe:
<list>
                     <item>1. To aſſemble the Congregation, to admoniſh &amp; cauſe the people to come together. <hi>Acts.</hi> 20. 17. 18. &amp; 14. 27. <hi>Ioel.</hi> 1. 13. 14. &amp; 2. 15. 16.</item>
                     <item>2. Inuocation, and vvorſhip of God for and vvith the Congregation: in a language vnderſtood. Vnder this duty are contained
<list>
                           <item>1. Confeſſion of ſinnes. <hi>Leu.</hi> 16. 29. 30. 31. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 28. <hi>Eſth.</hi> 9. 6.</item>
                           <pb n="44" facs="tcp:3348:28"/>
                           <item> 2 Petition. <hi>Act.</hi> 16. 13. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9. 3. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1.</item>
                           <item>3 Deprecation. <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2, 17.</item>
                           <item>4 Interceſſion. <hi>Act.</hi> 12. 5. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1.</item>
                           <item>5 Prayſe and thankſgiuing. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92. 1. 2. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 30. 21. <hi>Neh.</hi> 9. 5. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1.</item>
                           <item>6 Bleſſing of the people. <hi>Leu.</hi> 9. 22. 23. <hi>Numb.</hi> 6. 23. 24. 25. 26. 27. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 30. 27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. 26.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 To reade the Scriptures and that euery Sabbaoth; and and that alſo in a language vnderſtood by the people. <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 15. &amp; 15. 21. <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 16. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 27. 2. <hi>Chron</hi> 34. 30. <hi>Neh.</hi> 8. 3. 9.</item>
                     <item>4 To preach the word of God; <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 7. &amp; 16. 13. <hi>Mark.</hi> 1. 21. &amp; 6. 1. This he muſt performe, by preaching
<list>
                           <item>1 All the counſell of God: not keeping any thing backe that is profitable. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 20. 27. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 20.</item>
                           <item>2 Onely the word of God: the doctrine accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto godlineſſe, the true patterne of whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome words, the things that become holeſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 11. 1. <hi>Timot.</hi> 6. 3. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 1. Not fables, Philoſophy, profane &amp; vaine babbling, and oppoſitions of ſcience. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 4. &amp; 4. 7. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 8. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 20.</item>
                           <item>3 Faithfully, purely, and ſincerely. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 2. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 17. &amp; 4. 2. <hi>Ier.</hi> 23. 28. Neither pleaſing, or falſe, or ſtraunge doctrine: nor for vaineglory, contention or enuy. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 10. 9. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 13. 12. 18. 22. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 3 <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 17. <hi>Hebru.</hi> 13. 9. 2. <hi>Ioh. ver.</hi> 10. 2. <hi>Corin.</hi> 4. 5. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1. 14. 15.</item>
                           <item>4 Reuerently, grauely, and ſoberly handling it as the word of God, with reuerence and maieſtie, that it may carry authority and feeling power. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 20 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 5. &amp; 2. 13. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 15. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 11.</item>
                           <item>5 Zealouſly with feruency of ſpirit. <hi>Eſay,</hi> 58. 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 16. &amp; 18. 25. <hi>Io.</hi> 2. 17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 29. <hi>Acts.</hi> 18. 28.</item>
                           <item>6 Continually euery Sabbaoth. <hi>Luke</hi> 4. 16. <hi>Act.</hi>
                              <pb n="45" facs="tcp:3348:28"/> 17. 2. 3. &amp; 18. 4. 5. &amp; 13. 14. 15. 42. 44. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 46. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 7. 8.</item>
                           <item>7 Painefully, by giuing attendance to priuate ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying, and reading, and diligently by publicke prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching on both morning &amp; euening of the Sabbaoth. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 92. 1. 2. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 12. 13. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 13. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 2. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 9. <hi>Pro.</hi> 27. 23. <hi>Act.</hi> 20 31. &amp; 18. 25.</item>
                           <item>8 Wiſely diuiding the Word aright. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 15. both firſt in giuing the ſenſe and cauſing the people to vnderſtand; <hi>Nehe.</hi> 8. 8. 12. as alſo, ſecondly, fitly applying it to the preſent eſtate of time, place and perſon: and giuing to euery one his portion. <hi>Luke,</hi> 12. 42. 2. <hi>Timot.</hi> 3. 16. &amp; 4. 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 9. This publicke duty hath fiue parts:
<list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>Doctrine of truth,</hi> to teach it and defend it. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 2, 3. &amp; 18, 4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 3, 4, 5, 11. 2. <hi>Tim,</hi> 3. 16.</item>
                                 <item>2 Inſtruction in righteouſneſſe &amp; exhortation. <hi>Act.</hi> 18. 4. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12 12. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16.</item>
                                 <item>3 Reprouing and rebuking ſinne with terror to the obſtinate, <hi>Io.</hi> 7. 23. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. &amp; 4. 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 15. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 20. <hi>Iude, ver.</hi> 23.</item>
                                 <item>4 Diſprouing, confuting, and conuincing error. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 23, &amp; 18, 3. 2. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 3. 16, and 4, 2. <hi>Titus,</hi> 1. 9.</item>
                                 <item>5 Comfort and conſolation: <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 46. 47. 48. 52. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 4. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 18.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>5 To miniſter the Sacraments: wherin he is to
<list>
                           <item>1 Deliuer that which he hath receiued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23.</item>
                           <item>2 Baptize
<list>
                                 <item>1. The Children of belieuing Parents: requiring it. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 38. 39. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 14.</item>
                                 <item>2. With inuocation &amp; exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 16. 13, 15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19, 20. <hi>Io.</hi> 7. 23.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>3 Celebrate the Lords Supper, with
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3348:29"/>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1. Publique exhortation and inuocation. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 7. &amp; 2. 42. and ſinging of Pſalmes, <hi>Matthew</hi> 26. 30.</item>
                                 <item>2 Priuate
<list>
                                       <item>1 Inſtruction, admoniſhment, and direction to the ignorant and vnpraepared, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 30. 15. 16. 15. 18. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 28.</item>
                                       <item>2 Putting back the vnworthie. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22. 26. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 8.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>6 To Catechiſe the children of his charge, and inſtruct them in information of the Lord. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5. 12. and 6. 1. <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 4. 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Galath.</hi> 6. 6. <hi>Marke</hi> 10. 14. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>III. The people: or whole Congregation; who are called the people of God. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 10. and of Gods paſture. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95. 7. his ſheep, <hi>Ibide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> his ſeruants. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 16. his Church. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 5. 15. his inheritance. <hi>Iſay</hi> 19. 25. Kingdome of Chriſt. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 2. The body of Chriſt, which is the head thereof. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1. 18. 24. A choſen generation, a royall Prieſthood, an holy nation, a peculiar people, that they ſhould ſhew forth the vertues of him, that hath called them out of darkeneſſe into his maruellous light. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. They therfore muſt alſo keep holy the Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth. 1. Both to the honor of Chriſt the Lord of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth. <hi>Matt.</hi> 12. 8. after whoſe excellent name they are called: and into whoſe name they were baptized. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19. <hi>Acts.</hi> 2. 38. &amp; 19. 5. 2. As alſo in reſpect of their owne ſpirituall profit, inſtruction, and comfort.</item>
               <item>The ſanctification of the Chriſtian Sabbaoth; by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is eyther
<list>
                     <item>1 Publique: the which is ſanctified by the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian people with publique meanes, and after a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and free manner; as it ought alwaies ſo long as the viſible Church remaineth, or a caſe of neceſſity enforce not the contrary.</item>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:3348:29"/>
                     <item> 2 Priuate: is ſuch as is performed by priuate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and after a priuate manner: namely, vvhen Chriſtians cannot ſanctifie the Sabbaoth publique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in regard of
<list>
                           <item>1 The abſence of Gods publique ordinaunces: as publique preaching, prayer &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>2 The times of common warre or perſecution.</item>
                           <item>3 A caſe of ineuitable &amp; moſt neceſſary trauell, which cannot be deferred or auoided: or in caſe of ſickneſſe, impriſonment, hard ſeruice, ſlauery, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, or captiuity of any particular perſon and the like caſe: wherin God accepteth our holy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and honeſt indeuor according to that we haue, and not according to that we haue not.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>The publique ſanctifying of the Chriſtian Sabbaoth, ſtandeth in duties eyther
<list>
                           <item>affirmatiue.</item>
                           <item>negatiue.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>The duties affirmatiue are ſuch as Chriſtians are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded and tyed in conſcience to performe: and are eyther works of
<list>
                           <item>1 Piety.</item>
                           <item>2 Mercy.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>The works of Pyety are performed eyther
<list>
                           <item>1 In the duties themſelues, beeing mayne and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect worſhips of God.</item>
                           <item>2 In the circumſtances tending to the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of them.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>*1. The duties themſelues of Pyety to be performed by the Chriſtian people are theſe:
<list>
                     <item>1 To hearken to Gods word preached publiquely by a lawfull &amp; authorized Teacher. This they are required to doe, with
<list>
                           <item>1 Feare, reuerence, and humility. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 66. 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5. 7. <hi>Num.</hi> 16. 22.</item>
                           <item>2 Ioy, gladneſſe, and cheerefulneſſe. <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 48. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 6.</item>
                           <pb n="48" facs="tcp:3348:30"/>
                           <item> 3 Attention, diligence, heede, and watchfulneſſe. <hi>Act.</hi> 16. 14. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4. 17. <hi>Luke,</hi> 4. 20. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19.</item>
                           <item>4 Faith, conſent, and application of the doctrine and vſes. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 17. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Luke</hi> 4. 22, &amp; 7, 35. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 34. <hi>Io.</hi> 10. 26. 27. <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 48. &amp; 28. 24. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 13.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. To receaue the Sacrament of the Lords Supper; as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as thou mayſt. <hi>Act.</hi> 16. 13. 15. &amp; 20. 7. This muſt be performed, with
<list>
                           <item>1 Repentance; examining &amp; iudging ourſelues: and with a good conſcience. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 21. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 28 <hi>Mark.</hi> 1. 4. 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 30. 19.</item>
                           <item>2 Faith and application. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16. 16. <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 37. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 28. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 3. 4. <hi>Io.</hi> 6. 63. 64. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 26. 27.</item>
                           <item>3 Loue, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 17. &amp; 11. 18. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 41. 42 46. <hi>Io.</hi> 13. 2. 35. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 13.</item>
                           <item>4 Thankefulneſſe. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 26, 30. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 25. 26. 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 30. 15, 21. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 16.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Alſo remember alwayes to bee praeſent at the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of infants. 1. That thou may eſt omit no part of the publick worſhip of God, but pray with the Church and Congregation. 2. That thou may eſt outwardly grace Gods ordinaunce and countenance it (as it were) with thy praeſence, and not diſgrace, or ſeeme to ſcorne it by turning thy backe vnto it. 3. That Gods pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke ordinance may bee publickely not priuately per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, 4. That thou alſo may eſt hereby call to mind thy Couenant with God in Baptiſme, and Gods coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant made with thee: and examine what fruit thereof appeares within thee, that thou may eſt bleſſe God, if thou finde the ſame effectuall; and be humbled to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour vnto it if thou finde it to be ſmall.</item>
                     <item>3. To pray to God and prayſe him. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 19. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1. 2. This duty muſt alſo be done, with
<list>
                           <pb n="49" facs="tcp:3348:30"/>
                           <item>1 <hi>Humility:</hi> and ſenſe of Gods purity &amp; our owne vnworthineſſe. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 2. 11. &amp; 145. 19. <hi>Luke</hi> 18. 13. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56. 15. &amp; 66. 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 17. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5. 7.</item>
                           <item>2 <hi>Senſe and feeling of our wants,</hi> with hunger and deſire of obtaining them. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 17. &amp; 38. 9. <hi>Neh.</hi> 1. 11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 6. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11. 13.</item>
                           <item>3 <hi>Feruency and heartineſſe: Iames</hi> 5. 16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. 1. &amp; 119. 5.</item>
                           <item>4 <hi>Faith &amp; perſwaſion of obtaining,</hi> vpon Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull nature &amp; promiſes. 1. <hi>Io.</hi> 5. 14. &amp; 3. 22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 22. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. 8. &amp; 38. 15. &amp; 55. 17.</item>
                           <item>5 <hi>Loue,</hi> vnto our neighbour vnfeined. <hi>Mark.</hi> 11. 25. 26. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 7. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 8.</item>
                           <item>6 <hi>Holineſſe of life, and a good conſcience:</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 19. 22. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 8. 1. <hi>Io.</hi> 3. 22. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15. 7. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1. 15. <hi>Iob.</hi> 22 23. 27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66. 18.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 To ſing the Pſalmes and ſpirituall ſonges indited by the holy-Ghoſt. The vvhich duty becauſe it is a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall part of Gods worſhip (thoſe duties and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons beeing performed and required in ſinging of pſalmes, which are performed and required in prayer) wee are therefore to attend vnto it with all care and conſcience, by how much the more it is neglected commonly. Herein theſe duties are commaunded: that namely it be performed
<list>
                           <item>1 <hi>With vnderſtanding.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47. 7.</item>
                           <item>2 <hi>With</hi> heart and ſpirit. 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 14. 15. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Epheſ</hi> 5. 19.</item>
                           <item>3 <hi>With a grace and decency. Col.</hi> 3. 16.</item>
                           <item>4 <hi>With</hi> melody, mirth, inſtruction, and comfort to ourſelues. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 19. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Iam.</hi> 5. 13.</item>
                           <item>5 Vnto the Lord in a direct intention, beeing ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected as the matter of the Pſalme, and our owne prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent eſtate doth occaſion: this being alſo (as before is ſaid) a part of Gods worſhip. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 19. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</hi> 5. 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. 17. &amp; 30. 4. &amp; 47. 6. &amp; 92. 1. &amp; 111. 1. &amp; 137. 4.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:3348:31"/>
               <item> 2. The circumſtances tending to the better performance of theſe worſhips of God: and they are to bee conſidered according to the times; which are,</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1 Before the exerciſe of the Word and Prayer;
<list>
                     <item>1 Riſing early, both fitly to prepare our ſelues: as alſo to conſecrate as much of the Lords day vnto the Lords ſeruice and worſhip as we can. <hi>Ier.</hi> 7. 25. &amp; 32. 3. <hi>Mark.</hi> 1. 35. with ver. 38. 39. <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 1.</item>
                     <item>2 Examining of our conſciences, and confeſſing of our ſinnes to God: that wee may bring into the preſence of God, and aſſembly of the Saints, the peace of a quiet heart. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 28. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 31. To the which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a taking heede vnto our wayes, and a carefull ſtudy of holineſſe the whole weeke before. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 15. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1. 15.</item>
                     <item>3 To ioyne with our families in priuate prayer: or if our eſtate and condition be not ſuch, yet by our ſelues to pray feruently vnto God. 1. Both for our ſelues that we may bee profitable hearers for vnderſtanding, memory, grace and a bleſſing of the word. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 18. <hi>Prou.</hi> 2. 3. 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 7. <hi>Luke,</hi> 11. 13. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 5. 2. As alſo for our Teachers and Inſtructors that God would giue them vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance, that they may ſpeak as they ought. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 19. 20 <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 3. 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 18.</item>
                     <item>4 To diſpatch, vvith all effectuall care and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, all neceſſary buſineſſe, and put-by vnneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that wee or ours be not hindred from comming or timely comming: but that we with our houſholdes may ſerue God. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 24. 15. To this end the Houſholder muſt get fit ſeruants. <hi>Pſal</hi> 101. 6. and command them. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 19.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2 In the exerciſe; both afore and after noone: that thou maieſt giue to Chriſt all his owne day. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92. 1. 2. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58. 13.
<list>
                     <item>1 To come at the beginning to ioine to the preſent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes: and there continewe to the end, thou and thine. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 46. 10. <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 2. 33. &amp; 13 44. &amp; 20. 7. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4. 17
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3348:31"/> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 16. 19. <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 21. 1. <hi>King</hi> 8, 54. 55.</item>
                     <item>2 Such behauiour as becommeth Saints: tendeth to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification: and is guided by the rule of decency. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 13. &amp; 14. 26. 40. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 3. 4. Namely:
<list>
                           <item>1 Head vncouered, and knee and body bowed: 1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 11. 7. 25. <hi>Neh.</hi> 8. 6. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 9. 24. <hi>Acts.</hi> 9. 40. &amp; 20. 36.</item>
                           <item>2 Lifting vp the heart at the publicke prayers; to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> vnto them: <hi>Neh.</hi> 8. 6. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 16.</item>
                           <item>3 To note with penne the doctrines, or with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to obſerue the diuiſion, coherence, doctrine, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and proofes. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 11. To the end thou maiſt eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew ſleepe: and wandring thoughts; and ſo to heare with vnderſtanding, delight, and profit. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 15. 16. 19. &amp; 6. 20. &amp; 10. 15. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58. 13. <hi>Luke</hi> 8. 18.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3 After the exerciſe of the fore and after noon, we muſt be careful of theſe: <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Sobriety of meat and drink, and carefull temperance aboue all other times: that the body may bee ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and better diſpoſed to the duties of godlineſſe; not ouer burdened and made vnapt to remember, meditate, conferre, or hearken and giue heede. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 21. 29. 30. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 1. 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 17. <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 34.</item>
                     <item>2 Holy conference with other: either
<list>
                           <item>1 By occaſion at the table: whether of the things deliuered that day by the Preacher: or elſe of ſome other good matter miniſtred: auoiding the common rocke (vvhereupon men ſtumble) of profane and worldly talk: remembring the rule. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58. 13. <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 1. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11. 12. 15. 16.</item>
                           <item>2 By purpoſe and intention: calling our family together and examining them: or ioyning to other like minded Chriſtians, and mutually conferring of that which wee haue heard. <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 14. 5. 17. <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 11.</item>
                           <pb n="52" facs="tcp:3348:32"/>
                           <item> 3 Praier for a bleſſing of this our labour, and for grace effectually to performe the particular duties we haue bin taught this day. <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. 37. 38.</item>
                           <item>4 Singing of Pſalms in priuate. <hi>Act</hi> 16. 25. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 19.</item>
                           <item>5 A time for priuate reading of the Scripture, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 1. 1. 2. &amp; 119. 11. 15. 97.)
<list>
                                 <item>1 Of our owne
<list>
                                       <item>1 Sinnes. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 59. <hi>Iam.</hi> 3. 2</item>
                                       <item>2 Wants. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1. 12.</item>
                                       <item>3 Infirmities. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 7. 8. 9. 10</item>
                                       <item>4 Miſeries. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 19.</item>
                                       <item>5 Profitings in grace &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 18.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 Of the eſtate of the Church of GOD, whether in the ſtate of
<list>
                                       <item>1 Miſery.</item>
                                       <item>2 Mercy. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147. 20. <hi>Eſay</hi> 5. 4. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 23.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3 Of GOD his</item>
                              </list>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 Works of
<list>
                                       <item>Wiſedome.</item>
                                       <item>Power.</item>
                                       <item>Iuſtice.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 Benefits and mercies on our ſelues. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 116. 12. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 9. 10. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 12. 13.</item>
                                 <item>3 Word: eſpecially of the things which wee haue heard.
<list>
                                       <item>1 How much we vnderſtand and remember. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 1. &amp; 12. 5.</item>
                                       <item>2 What proofs we haue of it. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 23.</item>
                                       <item>3 How appliable to our ſelues euery thing is. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 21. <hi>Prou.</hi> 9. 12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. 12.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>6 Conſcience, care and heedfulneſſe to put in praeſent practiſe the doctrine &amp; vſes we haue heard reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred, &amp; ſo called to mind: with continuall &amp; feruent praier vnto God to work in vs the things that he hath taught vs. <hi>Io.</hi> 17. 13. <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 28. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 24.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>So much of the duties of Piety.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:3348:32"/>
               <item>*2. The workes of Mercy and neceſſity concerning ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<list>
                     <item>1 God and his worſhip: ſo it is lawfull on the Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 For Kings &amp; Magiſtrats, to cleanſe the Church of Idolatry. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 11. 15. 16. 18.</item>
                           <item>2 For the Prieſts of the olde Teſtament, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell, to doe ſuch neceſſary buſineſſe as tendeth to the worſhip of God. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 5.</item>
                           <item>3 For a Miniſter in teaching, or Chriſtians in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, to ouer-watch themſelues and to breake their ſleep. <hi>Act.</hi> 27. 8, 9.</item>
                           <item>4 To trauell on the Sabbaoth to heare the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of Gods word: or to performe a neceſſary deede of Mercy: vvhich caſes properly doe make a Sabbaoth dayes iourney. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 4. 23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. 6. 7.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 Gods Church: in ſuch like actions as theſe;
<list>
                           <item>1 To fight againſt the enemies of God in lawfull battell. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 20. 29. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 6. 15. [1. <hi>Maccabees</hi> 2. 34] and to do ſuch other needfull publick buſineſſe, as can admit no longer delay.</item>
                           <item>2 To put to death an idolatrous and euill deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing perſon, whoſe longer life may be daungerous to the Church of God. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 11. 9. 16.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 Our ſelues: ſo is it lawfull for vs
<list>
                           <item>1 To eate and ſatisfie hunger, by vſing Gods creatures with thankſ-giuing and ſobriety, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 1. 3. 4. 5. 7. <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 1. <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 11. 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11. 34. 1. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 4. 4. <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 34.</item>
                           <item>2 Carying of a bed home, or the like action: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Gods glory, or obedience to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements vrging vs. <hi>Io.</hi> 5. 9. 11.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:3348:33"/>
                     <item> 4 <hi>Our Neighbour:</hi> in things concerning his
<list>
                           <item>1. Body.
<list>
                                 <item>1 To ſaue life. <hi>Mark.</hi> 3. 4 <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 11. 12. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7. 23.</item>
                                 <item>2 To heale. <hi>Io.</hi> 9. 14. Note that this doth not patronize
<list>
                                       <item>1 The labors of our calling on that day.</item>
                                       <item>2 Studie and looking a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>ter gayne.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3 To feed and ſend part of our aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. <hi>Neh.</hi> 8. 10. 11. 12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 42.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. Soule. To viſite, inſtruct, exhort, reproue, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 42. 43.</item>
                           <item>3. Goods
<list>
                                 <item>1 To ſaue, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 27.</item>
                                 <item>2 To giue and collect almes. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 2. Heere note, this almes or collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be performed
<list>
                                       <item>1 Cheerefully: <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 8. 2. <hi>Corin.</hi> 8. 11. 12. &amp; 9. 7.</item>
                                       <item>2 Liberally to our power, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 12. &amp; 9. 5. 6.</item>
                                       <item>3 Wiſely and diſcreetly. <hi>Galat.</hi> 6. 10. <hi>Prouer.</hi> 31. 6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 40. 45. &amp; 10. 41. 42.</item>
                                       <item>4 Continually and weekly. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1. 2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 16.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>5 Our Cattell. Leade him to water: lift him out of a pit, and the like caſes wherein is danger of the ſpoyle and caſting away of Gods liuing creatures, which may be preuented by our helpe. <hi>Matthew</hi> 12. 11. <hi>Luke</hi> 13. 15. &amp; 14. 5.</item>
                     <item>6 Generally any good deede or morall duty, to doe well on a Sabbaoth is a Sabbaoth dayes duty. <hi>Matthew</hi> 12. 2. <hi>Mark.</hi> 3. 4.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Negatiue:</hi> Things not to be done, but carefully auoyded, as profaning the Sabbaoth: in cauſing to break Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements. Namely, all ſinne either in nature or cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56. 2: Either committed againſt</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:3348:33"/>
               <item>1 The firſt Table: as
<list>
                     <item>1 To ſeeke, or to doe our owne will or wayes. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58. 13.</item>
                     <item>2 Idolatry. <hi>Ezech:</hi> 20. 24. &amp; 23. 37. 38.</item>
                     <item>3 Hypocriſie. <hi>Luke</hi> 13. 15.</item>
                     <item>4 Diſobedience to God euen in a light matter. <hi>Ex.</hi> 20. 10. <hi>Numb.</hi> 15. 32. 35.</item>
                     <item>5 An vnlearned, vnſufficient falſe teaching, man-pleaſing, lewd-liuing, or ſcandalous and vnſanctiſi. ed Miniſtery. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22. 26. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 6. <hi>Ier.</hi> 8. 9. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 22.</item>
                     <item>6 Contempt or loathing or perſecuting of Gods word, or of Gods faithfull Miniſtry. <hi>Ezec.</hi> 20. 21. 24 <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 45. 46. 50.</item>
                     <item>7 To trouble or hinder witting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or wilfully a worke or duty of the Sabbaoth: whether it bee of
<list>
                           <item>1 Pyety: as the preaching of the Word. <hi>Acts.</hi> 13. 45. 46.</item>
                           <item>2 Mercy: <hi>Luke</hi> 13. 14. 16.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>8 All things that hinder the worſhip of God, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part thereof: as prayer, the preaching or hearing of Gods word, the receiuing of the Sacraments: (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be in a caſe of a neceſſary work of mercy, with out the which our ſelues or others cannot be, or not wel be by any longer delay of time.) <hi>Ex.</hi> 16. 23. 24. 26 29. &amp; 35. 3. &amp; 15. 32. 35. Of theſe kind of vnlawfull hindrances are;
<list>
                           <item>1 The ordinary labours of our weeke dayes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 9. <hi>Ier.</hi> 17. 22. 24. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 23. 3. 8.</item>
                           <item>2 Harueſt worke, or bearing of burthens. <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. 15. <hi>Ier.</hi> 7. 22. 24.</item>
                           <item>3 Buying or ſelling wares or victuals, albeit offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſell (vnleſſe in an extraordinary caſe the wares to our great loſſe or hazard of vndooing ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly be ſpoyled: or vnleſſe we ſhall endanger our health by not buying victuals.) <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. 16. In which caſes prouidence would be required before,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3348:34"/> and repentance, vvith amendment of our negligence after.</item>
                           <item>4 Trauelling on the Sabbaoth for gayne or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 29. 30.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2 The ſecond Table:
<list>
                     <item>1 Murder: profanenes, vpon the Sabbaoth. <hi>Mark.</hi> 3. 4. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 23. 37. 38.</item>
                     <item>2 Couetouſneſſe, oppreſſion, and worldly cares, luſts and deſires. <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 5. 6. <hi>Luke</hi> 21 34.</item>
                     <item>3 Adultery. <hi>Ezec.</hi> 23. 37.</item>
                     <item>4 Debate and contention. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58. 3. 4.</item>
                     <item>5 Vaine words. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58. 13.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>So much of the publicke ſanctifying of the Sabbaoth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The priuate ſanctifying of the Chriſtian Sabbaoth, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed priuately and by priuate perſons; namely, when Chriſtians can by no meanes enioy the benefit of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique means: which caſe becauſe it is a iudgement and heauy plague of God, both by withdrawing light, and leauing vs in darkneſſe: Chriſtians in this eſtate are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theſe rules:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 To be greatly humbled and to mourne, for abſence from the Church aſſemblies, Communion of Saints, and meanes of ſpiritual nouriſhment, direction and comfort: as alſo in reſpect of the profanations of Gods Sabbaoths by the wicked. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42. 4. &amp; 120. 5. &amp; 137. 4. 5. <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. 7. &amp; 2. 6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 136.</item>
               <item>2 To long for earneſtly and hunger with zealous and continuall deſire of minde, after the fruition and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying of ſo great a benefit. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 42. 2. &amp; 84. 1. 2. 3. 4. 10.</item>
               <item>3 To vſe all poſſible good meanes to come by the publique ordinaunces of God vpon the Sabbaoth: and eſteeme it as a rich benefit, worthy of all endeuour to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it
<list>
                     <item>1 By earneſt intreaty &amp; carefull ſuit vnto the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and gouernors, by whoſe authority they are permitted and encouraged; as alſo to the Teachers
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3348:34"/> themſelues. <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 42. <hi>Io.</hi> 4. 40. <hi>Ier.</hi> 38 9. 10. and 26. 17. 18. 19. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 22. 8. <hi>Exod.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>Neh.</hi> 1. 11. &amp; 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8.</item>
                     <item>2 By feruent and continuall prayer vnto God, the Lord of the harueſt, both to thruſt out faithfull labourers into his harueſt; as alſo to make vs eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly partakers of the ſame. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. 38. &amp; 24. 20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 4.</item>
                     <item>3 By kinde intreating, incouraging, defending and maintaining of the godly learned Preacher: and ſo to purchaſe to our ſelues this pearle or treaſure &amp; that gifte of God vnto his Church for the gathering of the Saints, and edification of the body of Chriſt: <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 6. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 12. 13. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 7. 8. 11. 13. 14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 10. 11. 14. 40. 41. &amp; 13. 44. 45. 46. <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 23. 23. Elſe, where the duty is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, a iuſt and heauy iudgement followeth. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3. 17. <hi>Mark.</hi> 3. 5. <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 4. &amp; 8. 34. <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 46. &amp; 19. 19.</item>
                     <item>4 By ſeeking with great hunger &amp; feruent deſire, and trauailing abroad (how-euer painefull or coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it may prooue) to redeeme and enioy this benefite: Remembring that is a Sabbaoths day iourney to worſhip God and to heare a Sermon. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 4. 23. <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 11. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 4. <hi>Prou.</hi> 8. 33. &amp; 2. 4. 5. <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 12. and to ſuffer much affliction to enioy this bleſſing 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 42.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>4 To vſe and put in practiſe all the meanes within our power, that are commaunded of God, or practiſed by the godly: wherein wee are carefully
<list>
                     <item>1 To double our priuate diligence in the abſence of the publicke meanes.</item>
                     <item>2 To obſerue as carefully the whole day, both fore and after-noon, as if the publicke meanes were preſent: conſidering the perpetuall equity of theſe Commaundements. <hi>Ex.</hi> 20. 8. 9. 10. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58. 30. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:3348:35"/> 16. 1. 2. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 92. 1. 2. The priuate practiſe of the Lords day is eyther performed,
<list>
                           <item>1 With others: as in a family: or conſent of practiſe by willing and vnited Chriſtians: in which caſes are required a ſpending of the day, in
<list>
                                 <item>1 Examination, inſtruction, and Catechiſme. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 7. 20. 21. and 11. 19. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 4.</item>
                                 <item>2 Conference and godly queſtioning and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering. <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 14. 17. 18. <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 6.</item>
                                 <item>3 Prayer, with thankſgiuing and praiſe. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 20. yea with faſting, on fit occaſions. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 31. 13. <hi>Heſt.</hi> 4. 16.</item>
                                 <item>4 Singing of Pſalmes. <hi>Act.</hi> 16. 25. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 19.</item>
                                 <item>5 Reading of Scriptures. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 11. <hi>Malac.</hi> 3. 16.</item>
                                 <item>6 Deedes and duties of mercy, collections, viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, comfortings. <hi>Matt.</hi> 25. 34. 35. 36. 37. 38. 39. 40.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 With our ſelues alone: as in a caſe of trauelling, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, hard ſeruice, or ſlauery: in which later caſes wee are by humble intreaty to ſeeke</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Liberty of ſanctifying the Lords day. Herin are required theſe things, or ſo much as is within our power, all or the moſt:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Meditation</hi> of our ſinnes: Gods word and works of wiſdome, power, Iuſtice, mercy, ſtate of the Church to reioyce or grieue at it, according as it is. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119. 58. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92. 5. 6. 9. 12. 13. and 1. 2.</item>
               <item>2 <hi>Prayer,</hi> and thankeſgiuing vnto GOD. <hi>Matt.</hi> 6. 6. <hi>Iames</hi> 5. 13. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 24. 63. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 17. 18. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 17.</item>
               <item>3 <hi>Singing Pſalmes: Iam.</hi> 5. 13. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 57. 7. &amp; 77. 6. <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 46.</item>
               <item>4 Reading of the Scriptures. <hi>Ioſhua</hi> 1. 8. <hi>Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> 3. 16.</item>
               <item>5 Workes of mercy, according to our power, and fit occaſion. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 12. <hi>Mark.</hi> 12. 41. 42. 43. 44.</item>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:3348:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item> 6 To ioine prayer with faſting (if neede bee) to bee humbled for ſinnes or iudgement: or to farther pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for our neceſſities. <hi>Neh.</hi> 1. 4. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 3.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>So much of the priuate ſanctifying of the Chriſtian Sabbaoth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Motiues,</hi> reaſons, and incouragements to the cheerefull and faithful obſeruation of the Lords day or Chriſtian Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth: and deterring vs from the profanation of the ſame; both in reſpect of</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Bleſſings obtained.</item>
               <item>2 Eſcaping iudgements.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Bleſſings</hi> and promiſes obtained.
<list>
                     <item>1 Concerning the life to come.
<list>
                           <item>1 Priuate: vrged to perſons in priuate:
<list>
                                 <item>1 It is a good worke. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92. 1.</item>
                                 <item>2 Sabbaoth exerciſes, commaunded of God, are bleſſed &amp; ſanctified vnto vs of God. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 10. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2. and a meanes of our ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. 13. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 20. 12.</item>
                                 <item>3 Gods acceptation of our Prayer and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in ſanctifying it. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56. 8.</item>
                                 <item>4 Planting vs in his Church, as flouriſhing plants. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56. 7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92. 13.</item>
                                 <item>5 An heart to delight in God. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58. 14.</item>
                                 <item>6 Ioy of the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56. 7.</item>
                                 <item>7 Aſſurance and ſecurity of Gods election. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56. 3. 4.</item>
                                 <item>8 Saluation and bleſſedneſſe. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56. 2. &amp; 58. 14.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 Publicke: The flouriſhing of the Church of God. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 17. 26. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. 2. 11. 12.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 Concerning this life.
<list>
                           <item>1 Publick. A flouriſhing Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth with other temporal &amp; earthly bleſſings; To the Kings, Nobles, ſubiects and whole eſtate. <note n="*" place="margin">
                                 <hi>Ier.</hi> 1 <hi>Leui.</hi> 26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6. 7.</note>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 Priuate: It gaineth vs, and ours, lawfull reſt of minde &amp; body from the paines and labours of our calling. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 10. &amp; 23. 12. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 14.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:3348:36"/>
               <item> 2 Curſes, plagues and iudgements following the profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Sabbaoth, which (by obſeruing it) wee doe eſcape. Heerein wee are to conſider, touching the profaning of the Lords Sabbaoth by negligence or wilfulneſſe,
<list>
                     <item>1 What it bringeth:
<list>
                           <item>1 The guilt of a great and grieuous ſinne: to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate the conſtitution and practiſe of the inſpired Apoſtles. 1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 16. 1. 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 7. To forget that which God bids remember: to profane that which hee bids keepe holy; to labour in that day which he bids reſt: to vnhallow that which he bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 8. 9. 10. 11. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22. 26.</item>
                           <item>2 It is an heauy puniſhment of God, and a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of Idolatry and falſe Prophets; for God to giue vs ouer to profane his Sabbaoths. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. 5. 11. <hi>Lamentations</hi> 2. 6. 14.</item>
                           <item>3 It bringeth Gods great plague, and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth wrath and guilt vpon the Magiſtrate, people, and whole eſtate of the Common-wealth. <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. 18. <hi>Ier.</hi> 17. 27. <hi>Ezec.</hi> 20. 13. Namely:
<list>
                                 <item>1 Sickneſſe. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. 2. 16.</item>
                                 <item>2 Famine. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. 2. 16. 19. 20. 26. 29</item>
                                 <item>3 Warre. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. 2. 25. 36. 37.</item>
                                 <item>4 Enemies rule, tyranny, and triumph ouer vs. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. 2. 17.</item>
                                 <item>5 Wilde beaſts. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. 2. 22.</item>
                                 <item>6 Captiuity. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 20. 23. 24. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. 2. 33. 34.</item>
                                 <item>7 Encreaſe of plagues. <hi>Leuiticus</hi> 26. 2. 18. 21. 24. 28.</item>
                                 <item>8 Vtter deſolation and ouerthrowe of the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3348:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> whole eſtate of the Common-wealth. <hi>Ier.</hi> 17. 27. <hi>Amos.</hi> 8. 5. 6. 7. 8. 10. <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. 18. <hi>Leu.</hi> 26. 2. 32. 34. 38.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>4 It finally bringeth euen vnto the Church theſe euils;
<list>
                                 <item>1 Famine of the Word. <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 5. 6. 11. 12.</item>
                                 <item>2 God abhorring and not accepting our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. <hi>Amos</hi> 5. 21. 22. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1. 11. 12. 13. 14. 15.</item>
                                 <item>3 Vtter deſolation of the Church of God. <hi>Lam.</hi> 2. 6.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>5 The bodily death, for the breach of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, did figure vnto vs the death of the ſoule for the breach of the Morall part of the Sabbaoth. For the curſe remaineth ſtill. <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. 14. 15. &amp; 35. 2. <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. 26. <hi>Galath.</hi> 3. 10.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 What it maketh and marketh men to bee in the eyes of God:
<list>
                           <item>1 Generally in all ſorts.</item>
                           <item>2 Particularly in the Clergie.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1 In the people and all perſons whatſoeuer:
<list>
                     <item>1 They are not of God which keep not his Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth. <hi>Io.</hi> 9. 16.</item>
                     <item>2 They are fooles and vnwiſe that do profane and not ſanctifie the Sabbaoth. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92. 1. 6.</item>
                     <item>3 Vnbelieuers, vagabond and wicked fellows are enemies and hinderers of the ſanctifying of the Sabbaoth. <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 5. 17.</item>
                     <item>4 They are Hypocrites that are offended at the keeping holy of the Sabbaoth. <hi>Luke</hi> 13. 14. 15.</item>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:3348:37"/>
                     <item> 5 They are enemies of God and of his Church, that mocke at the Sabbaoth of the Lord. <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. 7.</item>
                     <item>6 They are ſuch as iudge themſelues vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of euerlaſting life, that do hinder or perſecute the ſanctifying of the Sabbaoth day. <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 45. 46. 50.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2 In the Clergie and ſpirituall ſort.
<list>
                     <item>1 It ariſeth of groſſe and wilfull ignorance in the Clergy, if they do not rightly ſanctifie the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth of God; and deſerueth iuſt reproofe. <hi>Matt.</hi> 12. 3. 5. 7.</item>
                     <item>2 They are a wicked Clergie and vtterly diſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked &amp; reproued by God, that hide their faces from keeping the Lords Sabbaoth holy, and ſo profane it. <hi>Ezec.</hi> 22. 26. &amp; 46. 2. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 6.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>MATTHEVV 12. 8.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Sonne of Man is Lord of the Sabbaoth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
